<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The preacher, or the art and method of preaching: shewing the most ample directions and rules for invention, method, expression, and books whereby a minister may be furnished with such helps as may make him a useful laborer in the Lords vineyard. / By William Chappell Bishop of Cork, sometime Fellow of Christs College in Cambridge.</title>
            <title>Methodus concionandi. English</title>
            <author>Chappell, William, 1582-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1707_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209506</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868383</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170289</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78576)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170289)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 212:E1707[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The preacher, or the art and method of preaching: shewing the most ample directions and rules for invention, method, expression, and books whereby a minister may be furnished with such helps as may make him a useful laborer in the Lords vineyard. / By William Chappell Bishop of Cork, sometime Fellow of Christs College in Cambridge.</title>
                  <title>Methodus concionandi. English</title>
                  <author>Chappell, William, 1582-1649.</author>
                  <author>Brough, W. (William), d. 1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 204, [12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edw. Farnham, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head Palace neer Corn-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Methodus concionandi.</note>
                  <note>Editor's preface signed: Phil. Christianus, i.e. William Brough.</note>
                  <note>The last six leaves bear "A nomenclator of sundry tracts, sermons, and commentaries ...".</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "March 24"; "March".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Preaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170289:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The PREACHER,</hi> OR THE Art and Method OF PREACHING: SHEWING The moſt ample Directions and Rules for Invention, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, Expreſſion, and Books whereby a Miniſter may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with ſuch helps as may make him a Uſeful Laborer in the Lords Vineyard.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM CHAPPELL Biſhop of <hi>Cork,</hi> ſometime Fellow of Chriſts College in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>If any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the Oracles of God,</p>
               <bibl>1 Pet. 4.11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edw. Farnham,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Popes-head Palace</hi> neer <hi>Corn-hill,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170289:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170289:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170289:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170289:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His elaborate peece of the Reverend Author <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Chappell,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cork,</hi> coming to my hands, and conſidering the great advantage the Church of God might reap by it in this Spiritual infatuated age wherein we live; the Lords Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard being great, and the skilful and painful Labourers few, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof moved me to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to publick view, hoping it may have that deſired effect the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Author intended it to, <hi>viz.</hi> for the well inſtructing and fitting of young Proficients, in Divinity, to the work of the Miniſtry, that they might by the bleſſing of the Lord, upon their endeavours, and theſe directions,
<pb facs="tcp:170289:4"/> ſpeak in due ſeaſon, as the Oracles of God, labouring in the heavenly calling as workmen that need not be aſhamed; which that it may have its deſired effect, is the hearty deſire and expectation of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Phil. Chriſtianus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170289:4"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of Books Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and to be ſold by <hi>Edw. Farnham</hi> at his ſhop entring into <hi>Popes-head Palace</hi> out of <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Britains Triumph,</hi> or a Hiſtory of the Wars and other affairs of <hi>Britain,</hi> from the death of the late King to the third year of the Lord Protector.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Compleat Doctreſs,</hi> or a Treaty of Womens Diſeaſes, and their Cures.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170289:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Argalus &amp; Parthenia,</hi> by <hi>Fran. Quarls.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The New-England Pſalms.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Statue Unbowelled,</hi> being a choiſe Treatiſe of Natural Philoſophy in <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Divine Bloſſomes,</hi> or the Yong mans Proſpective. A Poem.</item>
               <item>The Works of Mr. <hi>John Milton,</hi> concerning <hi>Divorce,</hi> digeſted into one Volume.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Converſion of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:170289:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170289:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170289:6"/>
            <head>Analyſis of the whole Book.</head>
            <p>Of the Method of Preaching:
<list>
                  <item>the Definition, Chap. 1.</item>
                  <item>the parts of it
<list>
                        <item>the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<list>
                              <item>Preparation thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<list>
                                    <item>the ingreſs or entrance to the meaning of the place of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture in which it is contained, Chap. 2.</item>
                                    <item>the placing thereof, where
<list>
                                          <item>what Doctrine is, Chap. 3.</item>
                                          <item>How it ought to be laid, Ch. 4. to 11. incluſively.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>Handling of it
<list>
                                    <item>direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in
<list>
                                          <item>Explication, Chap. 12.</item>
                                          <item>Confirmation ſhewing <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                                                <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                             </gap>
                                             <list>
                                                <item>
                                                   <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                                                      <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                                   </gap>,</item>
                                                <item>
                                                   <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                                                      <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                                   </gap>,</item>
                                             </list> Chap. 13.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>by Vindication from objections, Ch. 14.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>the Uſe, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<list>
                              <item>in general, Chap. 15.</item>
                              <item>Specifically con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the
<list>
                                    <item>Minde, as
<list>
                                          <item>Inſtruction, Chap. 16.</item>
                                          <item>Refutation, Chap. 17.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Heart
<list>
                                          <item>in its preſent diſtemper by
<list>
                                                <item>Reproof,</item>
                                                <item>Comfort.</item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                          <item>in reſpect of the future
<list>
                                                <item>good, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, Chap. 20.</item>
                                                <item>evill, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, Chap. 21.</item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:170289:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170289:7"/>
            <head>THE METHOD OF PREACHING.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Method of Preaching is a diſcourſe upon a Text of Scripture, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing its parts accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the order of nature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, the accord of them, one with the other may be judged of, and contained in memory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170289:8"/>
                  <head>Of the Crypticks, or Occultations of this Method in General.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. This Method may be hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den two wayes: Namely in ſhew only, or really. The firſt way is, when there is really a method, and the Preacher hath as it were a clew or line by which he is guided from the beginning to the end of his ſpeech without any ſtraying; yet this method is concealed from the hearers, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by not naming in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe heads he means to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon; and partly by not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing his tranſitions from one head to another, and laſtly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſing both the heads and their connexions under other terms and reſpects.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The latter way is, when the method is concealed really;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170289:8"/> and this may likewiſe be done two wayes, (for I would not ſet open a gap for digreſſions, or He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeneals) Firſt by omitting one or two of the principall parts. Secondly, by intermixing, or inverting the order. When and which way it muſt be done, ought to be the dictate of his own wiſdom.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. Of the ingreſs or entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Text of Scripture which is to be treated of.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſparts of the Method are of
<list>
                     <item>Doctrine</item>
                     <item>Uſe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170289:9"/>
               <p>In the Doctrine there ought to be conſidered the
<list>
                     <item>Preparation thereunto;</item>
                     <item>Handling of it.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In the Preparation the
<list>
                     <item>Entrance to the place where it is,</item>
                     <item>Laying of the doctrine it ſelf.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Of the Entrance. If the Preacher intendeth to treat upon ſome whole Book, Pſalm, or Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, he muſt firſt briefly ſhew the chief ſcope of the whole, and the parts (wherein is the chief uſe of the diſtribution of the whole into parts) in their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt extent. Then the parts of the firſt part, if it have any, and ſo proceed to the reſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Likewiſe if he undertake the greateſt part of ſome whole treaty: firſt let him ſhew the ſcope, then ſet down the parts,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170289:9"/> and ſhew how that part which he is to handle, hath its cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with the reſt, and tends to that ſcope: and let him conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that part, firſt in it ſelf, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly in its relation to the whole.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Laſtly, if he takes any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Text for a ſubject of a Sermon or two; if it be in the Context (as many in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs,</hi> &amp;c. are not) let him firſt ſhew the connexion of it, or the relation to the principal part to which it belongs: Or if it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins a treaty, let him ſhew firſt whereto that, whereof this is a member tends, and how this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth thereunto. And let that particular Text be conſidered firſt in it ſelf, next in the relation (if any) to that which precedes. See an example hereof, Chap 4. Sect. 6. &amp; Ch. 6. Sect. 17. and elſewhere.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170289:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. Of the rayſing of Doctrine.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHat Doctrine is I call Doctrine a divine axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome comprehended in the text. Of which definition (becauſe it ſeems to mean ſome novelty) I muſt give ſome reaſon for each particular part.</p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Axiome</hi>] for I lay this as a ground and foundation, That there is nothing true or falſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be an Axiome. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatſoever is revealed to us of Divine Truth (for there can be no falſehood in the Word of God) is contained in the Axiomes of holy Scripture.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Divine</hi>] For there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny axiomes in Scripture, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170289:10"/> are not divine, but enunciated by men, not ſpoken by the holy Ghoſt, yea ſome by the father of Lyes himſelf, yet this makes a divine axiome, that ſuch have ſaid ſuch things, Mat. 4.6. <hi>Saith unto him. Caſt thy ſelf down,</hi> he addes a motive, <hi>If thou be the Son of God;</hi> he alleadgeth divine teſtimony for his indemnity; <hi>For it is written, &amp;c.</hi> Which Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture rightly cited, all the devils of hell cannot make invalid. Which ſhall be better treated of in its proper place, for here we will only obſerve Satans fraud in the allegation and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>There are alſo in Scripture certaine feigned Propoſitions, which (by the ſpecial priviledge of Comparates) doe argue real Redditions, and being diſpoſed with their Redditions, doe make
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170289:11"/> divine axiomes (as alſo the parts of them, which belong to the ſcope, applyed to the parts of the Redditions) and yet the feigned Propoſitions, or their parts, conſidered of themſelves without their Redditions, doe not make divine Axiomes. As for example, the Parables of the Sower, and the Tares, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the explaining of which our Saviour applies the feigned To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick to the real. See Chap. 6. Sect. 16.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Comprehended in the Text</hi>] Not only deduced from it by a conſequence. For axiomes that are found in Scriptures may be called Prime truths, and as it were Principles, in reſpect of thoſe which are vertually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them, and may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from them by a good conſequence: And theſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170289:11"/> are they which I would on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have held for Doctrines, yet theſe are not to be had <hi>totidem verbis,</hi> or word by word formally in the text, and therefore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure not obvious to every one, or conſpicuous at the firſt ſight, but ſometimes are to be drawn out and reduced into form, the Explication being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, or a Collation with other Scriptures, preſuppoſing the common manner of ſpeaking, or the Wiſdom of God who ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Theſe I ſay I would have only to be held for Doctrines, for by this means, firſt hearers may grow accuſtomed to the Text of holy Scripture, when they are as it were led by the hand through all its axiomes, or expreſſe truths, whereas other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they may goe from the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon almoſt as ignorant in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170289:12"/> Text as they came. Secondly, by this means the hearer will have the Doctrine as it were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes; ſo that coming home, having opened the book, he may ſay, I have this day heard this part of holy Writ expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and applyed. Whereas the Doctrine being deduced by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence (oftentimes obſcurely, ſometimes weakly; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times falſely) is ſoon forgotten, or deſerves to be ſo, and by this means the foundation of the whole Sermon falls. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by this means the Preacher doth neceſſarily tye himſelf to the words of the Text, or at leaſt will not erre in the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his diſcourſe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as contrarywiſe, this curb being taken away, there is is a great way given to ſtraying, making any thing of what you will, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170289:12"/> applying ſome few general col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections to any text, (ſometimes to the connexion, before the Text it ſelf be underſtood) and ſo without touching, but meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglecting the Text, to the filling of the ears and mindes of the hearers with impertinent (and peradventure dangerous) opinions in ſtead of Doctrines. Fourthly, by this means the Reflexion of the Uſe in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate vertue of the Principle will be much more efficacious to convince and ſubject the hearers mindes, and may be with more confidence and authority urged by the Preacher. And contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rywiſe when a Uſe is inferred out of another Uſe by long and incertain conſequences, the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther every one is remote from its principle, ſo much the leſſe thereof it hath in it, and acts
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170289:13"/> ſo much the leſſe by its virtue. And ſo eaſily gives opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of evaſion to the hearers, and of ſaying (as they commonly doe, eſpecially in Reproofs) <hi>he ſtrayed far from his Text.</hi> Neither can the Preacher himſelf with any true confidence urge that which in the preſent words of his mandates (namely of the holy Scriptures) hath little or no confirmation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Although I ſhould here hardly admit of any Crypſis, yet I believe thoſe general ſayings of holy Scripture (propounded by God unto all, and whereof that of our Saviour may be taken, <hi>What I ſay unto you, I ſay unto all</hi>) which were written or ſpoken to ſome who were then living, ſo they receive no ſpecification from them, may alſo be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to our auditors, as directed to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170289:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. How a Doctrine ought to be laid.</head>
               <p>SEeing the Axiomes of holy Scripture are not framed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that notion which God hath of himſelf and others, but of that which he in his will hath conceived to be as a rule to us, that being attemperated to our mind, let it be enunciated to its Logical directrix. And an Axiome being a diſpoſal of an argument with an argument, and a Syllogiſm of two in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion with the third, and as the arguments are affected one with the other, ſo they actually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit their force in both places, it will be of much concernment
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170289:14"/> here, to know well and weigh the affections of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Text con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in it ſelf is either
<list>
                     <item>Axiomatical or,</item>
                     <item>Syllogiſtical.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>If axiomatical, there may be a Topical Analyſis premiſed, ſhewing firſt the <hi>Thema,</hi> or <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid,</hi> then the Arguments by which it is illuſtrated, and that in terms fitted to the Auditors capacity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Axiome (be it either ſimple or compounded) is either one alone; or contains more in it. If one alone, it may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any more adoe be preſently treated of. But if it contain more in it, they muſt particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be (as one may ſay) ſingled out and placed: this in the firſt, this in the ſecond, this in the third place, and ſo forward
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170289:14"/> according to the order of their nature.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This order ought not to be looked upon by the ſeries of the words, (to which it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes contrary) but by the natures of the things themſelves; in the eſtimating of which alſo one ought to be very cautulous. That Axiome that <hi>every cauſe by nature is before its effect,</hi> though it be true, may here give an occaſion of error, becauſe, as that which is cauſe, is, before it is a cauſe; ſo that whereof it is a cauſe, may be conſidered in an abſtract notion, before it is conſidered in relation to that cauſe in a ſpecial and diſtinct notion: Yea, peradventure the effect may be conceived under the notion of the ſubject, and the cauſe as an adjunct employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about it. As for example,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170289:15"/> 
                  <hi>By him all things are made,</hi> 1. <hi>All things were made.</hi> 2. <hi>By him.</hi> Yea though <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be before the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſubject before the adjunct; yet if the adjunct in its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion doth contain arguments, which of themſelves make a compleat ſenſe, and take their ſpecification from the ſubject, it ought in order firſt to be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of; as for example, <hi>To us a child is born:</hi> 1. <hi>A child is born.</hi> 2. <hi>To us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. But if we conſider the axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes in themſelves, it will not be difficult to find the order. Seeing that is firſt, which is moſt ſimple, and moſt general; not depending on the reſt, but the reſt on it. Likewiſe that in the ſecond place which immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depends on the firſt, and the reſt on it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if there be any collateral ones, it is all one
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170289:15"/> to the method which is treated of firſt; yet it will be the more commodious way to follow the ſeries of the words, and take that firſt in hand, which firſt offers it ſelf to the Readers view.</p>
               <p n="6">6. There may be ſome abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute thing in the parts of each axiome, that may contain a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. That which is abſolute in the parts, is to be handled before the parts be jointly treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of. The abſolute is to be conſidered according to the rule of its <hi>genus.</hi> Act. 27.23. <hi>For there stood by me this night the Angel of God, whoſe I am, and whom I ſerve.</hi> 1. <hi>The Apoſtle profeſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be Gods.</hi> 2. <hi>That he ſerves God.</hi> 3. <hi>That he is Gods, and ſerves him.</hi> 4. <hi>That the Angel of God, whoſe to be, and whom to ſerve be profeſſeth, ſtood by him that night:</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170289:16"/> the three firſt I call abſolutes in the antecedent. So in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, Matth. 1.21. <hi>He ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes.</hi> 1. <hi>His people have their ſins.</hi> 2. <hi>He will ſave his people,</hi> &amp;c. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative condition in <hi>for. Becauſe he ſhall doe this, you ſhall call his name Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. If by the influx of latter arts (namely Grammar, Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) into the Text, Logick cannot be immediately examined: then the words are firſt to be ſtript of thoſe arts by ſome general explication, and the ſenſe to be made plain, and ſo the way made ready for the Logical Analyſis and aſſignation of the axiomes that they may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be therein.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If the ſimple ones come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of the comparates (as Eccleſ. 5.1. Epheſ. 5 11.) or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170289:16"/> the comparates under the ſpecies of the ſimple, (as Prov. 8.10. Matth. 9.13.) or of another kind of comparates, then that which the note ſets forth, (as Heb. 12.24.) it is the Logicks part to propound the Axiome, pronuncing how the thing is. See an example, Chap. 7. Sect. 4. &amp; 9.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If in the foreſaid arts there be any thing involved concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any part of the axiome; it may be joyned with that part which it concerns, to make good the axiome. See an example, Sect. 16. If to the whole, (as in the figures of ſentences) that very ſame which is added, will make an axiome to be propoſed and treated of after that to which it is annexed, Proverbs 15.23. <hi>A word ſpoken in due ſeaſon, how good is it?</hi> 1. It is good.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170289:17"/> 2. Even to the admiration of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. But if thereby there chance to be any eſſential thing want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that ought to be ſupplyed out of the uſe of the phraſe and ſcope of that and the like places, the conſonancy of faith agreeing thereunto, Luk. 13.9. <hi>And if it bear fruit,</hi> namely, <hi>thou ſhalt let it ſtand;</hi> or ſome ſuch thing.</p>
               <p n="11">11. If the explication of ſome notion, in an axiome already laid, doe not neceſſarily multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply axiomes, and they are to be treated of: that notion is firſt to be unfolded, the axiomes to be drawn out, and their treaty to be inſtituted according to the preſcribed method. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, 2 Tim. 3.16. <hi>Scripture is profitable,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>for recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying.</hi> The heart of man may
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170289:17"/> be irregular, or ſtraying from the right and its rule two ways. Namely, by being exalted above the rule, or by being dejected beneath it, and therefore in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way it may want rectify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in the firſt by Reprehenſion or Reproof, in the latter by Conſolation or Comfort. 1. Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is good for Reproof. 2. For Comfort.</p>
               <p n="12">12. If in the reſolution of one axiome into many, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the words ſhall ſeem to be ſome obſtacle thereunto, it may be lawfull to alter it, ſo the ſame ſenſe remain. As for example. This, <hi>God created the heavens:</hi> In this, <hi>The heavens were created by God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Proverbiall ſpeeches or ſayings being oftentimes uttered <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, antithetically; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that they may compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170289:18"/> many things in a few, it is enough if they expreſſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the one part thereof, and leave the reſt to be underſtood in the other by vertue of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titheſis: which when it is ſo done, thoſe things which are deficient in the one part, may be ſupplyed out of the other, that ſo the whole and compleat ſenſe of the whole ſentence may be gathered. But becauſe thoſe things which are ſo ſupplyed, are not ſo manifeſtly contained in the Text, as thoſe which are expreſſed, therefore they may either be brought in as Uſes, or if as Doctrines, then muſt it clearly be ſhewen, how they proceed from the Text, and they muſt not be long inſiſted upon. There are many frequent exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hereof in <hi>Solomons</hi> Proverbs; and many not unlike thereunto
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170289:18"/> are to be found in divers parts of Scripture, as Pſal. 1. v. laſt, <hi>The Lord knoweth the way of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but the way of the ungodly ſhall periſh.</hi> 1. <hi>The Lord knoweth</hi> (that is to ſay, approveth) <hi>the way of the righteous.</hi> 2. (By the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite member) <hi>it ſhall be preſerved or proſpered.</hi> 3. <hi>God diſlikes the way of the ungodly</hi> (by firſt mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber). 4. It ſhall periſh.</p>
               <p n="14">14. In which places (either of the Proverbs or any other part of Scripture) ſomething in the one member, neceſſarily includes ſomewhat which is in the other, which may both be included and joyned into one axiome, and that is to be treated of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either part of the axiome in which they are to be found. See an example, Chap. 7. Sect. 4. &amp; Ch. 10. Sect. 2.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170289:19"/>
               <p n="15">15. Thoſe which being inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely ſet down, intend not a general truth, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as it were for the moſt part, are likewiſe to be propoſed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Behold</hi> ſet before ſome of the Lords words, doth argue that ſentence to deſerve a ſpecial attention. And from hence may be raiſed a doctrine of the latter conſideration, according to the rule, Sect. 9. An example hereof is, 1 Pet. 2.6. (the full treating whereof muſt be had from the rules of Comparates) where ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of the ſaid 9. Sect. (the Apoſtle expreſſing in the fourth verſe what is wanting) 1. ax. <hi>Chriſt is the ſtone in the head of the corner.</hi> 2. <hi>Elect and pretious.</hi> 3. <hi>God laid it,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in Sion.</hi> 4. <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth,</hi> &amp;c. 5. <hi>All theſe things
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170289:19"/> deſerve a moſt ſpecial attention.</hi> Of the ſame nature ſeems to be that of the Apoſtle, (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) but alwayes in matters of great moment.</p>
               <p n="17">17. The word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> added to a ſentence ſtrongly denieth, and doth moreover adde the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, being ſpoken by God, an abomination of the thing deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; if ſpoken by man together with it, ſometimes a deprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion. The ſame thing almoſt is ſignified by the Greek (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, let it not be ſo) ſee Ch. 8. Sect. 17.</p>
               <p n="18">18. You ought to apply your mind chiefly to that axiome, in which the efficacy or ſcope of the Text is placed: Thoſe which are acceſſory, may for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent be more ſlightly handled. For at another time there may fall a more apt place where they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170289:20"/> may be found as principals and chief.</p>
               <p n="19">19. That which I ſaid before concerning the order of axiomes, though it may ſeem ſtrange to ſome, yet none will ask me a reaſon of it, have he but any touch, and be never ſo little verſed in the Dialecticks, whoſe judgement and memory (I ſay nothing of the hearers) will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire an order; and who by this means will have, not only the firſt part of his diſcourſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in it ſelf, and diſtinct from the reſt; but will alſo in it, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his way to thoſe things which follow, in the fore requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite and generals of them. I will rather adviſe you to reſerve to each axiome, that which is Homogeneal to it, that the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may agree with the order of the axiomes.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170289:20"/>
               <p n="20">20. What ſhall we then ſay of that Topical (as I may call it) way of Preaching, and that oftentimes according to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the words, where each arguments, or Topical places, are propoſed as Doctrines, or foundations of the diſcourſe, eſpecially when each one carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſome kind of emphaſis with it?</p>
               <p>Though I am not ſo perverſe or nice, but that I can eaſily like of any way or manner of handling the Divine Word, ſo it be profitable: yet becauſe my intent is to enquire into the Method, I ſhall take leave to ſay ſomewhat of ſo uſual a one.</p>
               <p>And this in the firſt place. If ſuch Preachers did only doe that which they ſeem to propoſe, the whole Sermon, how long ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it were, would be but a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170289:21"/> meer explication; for thoſe naked and ſimple tearms are not capable of any farther act, as being not apt to contain (as we ſaid before) any thing of truth or falſehood. But ſuch a diſcourſe can neither be a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in the Text, nor any way fruitful to the Auditors. For becauſe the Argument, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in it ſelf, is only affected to argue, and that there is no act of judgement but where the argument is diſpoſed with an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, it is impoſſible to bring any proof, or inferre any uſe, of a bare argument.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that emphaticall word (if it be ſo, and not a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) hath the reſt of the Text, or ſome part thereof joyned with it, for a foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that part of the diſcourſe; oft times that which is by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170289:21"/> firſt and which if it ſhould be firſt treated of, would give a light to it: and alwayes that without which neither the ſenſe nor ſentence is compleated. Whence it comes, that it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo efficacious, nor convictive (that namely being not treated of, which is required for its foundation) nor ſo perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſcientifical, that being as yet concealed, which is by nature firſt, and ſhould carry a light before it. But as much as neceſſity forceth us to take on both ſides, that this may ſubſiſt and beclear, ſo much tautology and confuſion is brought forth, when the ſame thing is in the ſame manner repeated, and made both prior and poſterior to it ſelf. This ſeems harder when in an axiome conſiſting of an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct occupated, and a ſubject
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170289:22"/> (as there be many in Scripture) the adjunct, which ſometime is impiouſly applicable to other ſubjects, is firſt treated of: though it doe receive its ſpecification from the ſubject.</p>
               <p n="21">21. The remedy of this evill is, to ſelect, and conſtitute in the firſt place that axiome (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it conſiſt of two, or more arguments) which by nature is firſt, and contains in it ſelf the compleat, and independent ſenſe: and then joyn unto it that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which may make that axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome that by order of nature is next, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neither need the empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis to be feared, which may very well be cared for in treating of the axiome; namely, in ſuch fort that every ſeveral emphaſis, may have its due explication and proof, and the uſes be ſo inferred and diſpoſed, as they ſhall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170289:22"/> proceed from this or that emphaſis. Which may then time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be done, when the whole foundation is clearly explicated and proved: For then they may be urged in vigor of the whole, without any Tautology or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
               <div type="cryptic">
                  <head>Crypſis.</head>
                  <p n="22">22. Before any Doctrine be conſtituted, there may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed the Explication of the whole Text, and (if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire) a vindication from falſe Expoſitions: as, if it be ſome principal Text, which the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries of truth doe abuſe to confirm their opinions.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. Two or three axiomes may be joyned into one, when either the ſterility of the axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes, or almoſt the ſame ſenſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170289:23"/> expreſſed in various words, or the Preachers feſtination (either towards his ending or haſtening to ſome principal point) or ſome other ſuch like cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. One axiome <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually contained in the Text, may be inferred out of another, as a Uſe out of a Doctrine, as 1 Pet. 5.7. <hi>Caſting all your care upon him, for he careth for you.</hi> 1. Axjome, <hi>God careth for you.</hi> 2. Uſe of Exhortation, <hi>Caſt all your care upon him.</hi> 3. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative axiome, (<hi>viz. Becauſe he careth, therefore eaſt</hi>) may be made a motive in that exhortation. Likewiſe an axiome in the Text may be converted into a Uſe of the precedent axiome, as Pſal. 42.2. Axiome. <hi>God is a living God.</hi> Exhortation. <hi>Let our ſoul</hi> (with <hi>Davids</hi>) <hi>thirſt for the living God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170289:23"/>
                  <p n="25">25. If ſeverall axiomes be joyned together, it ſhall be free either to conſider them ſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, or with a diſtinct reſpect to each ſeverally. And the uſe of thoſe things which are leſſe eſſential to the principal ſcope, may be compendiouſly handled. But thoſe which are more chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended muſt be more fully followed.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. In thoſe verſes which have [<hi>Thus ſaith the Lord</hi>] or the <hi>Lord hath ſworn,</hi> &amp;c. the axiomes which are contained in the thing atteſted may be propoſed, and the witneſſe aſſevering them, be brought as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: and he to be ſo explained, as there may a force of proof appear thence, as from the name <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> The Lord ſaith, &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170289:24"/>
                  <p n="27">27. Thoſe things which have the word <hi>behold,</hi> ſometimes may be propounded as an axiome, that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Ecce,</hi> or Behold, ſhould adde to the precedent to which it belongs, and be as it were a bond connexing the uſes to the Doctrine, Behold this for Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for Reproof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="28">28. If any one (as it is the ordinary cuſtom of Churches beyond the Sea) doth take upon him a long text, he may be Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis diſtribute it into parts, and illuſtrate them, either ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally or joyntly, by ſome explication or paraphraſe, then chuſe the chief axiome of each part, or reduce the ſum of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of them into one, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the firſt member of the ſecond general Crypſeos ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate the treating of then to the time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170289:24"/>
                  <p n="29">29. If in framing axiomes out of ſome long ſentence, the order of nature ſhould overmuch diſturbe the order of words, ſome ſlight, diſtribution may be premiſed, whereby that incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience may be obviated: and having run over each part, the ſull ſenſe of the whole period may be expreſſed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. Of Axiomes in Specie.</head>
               <p>Afingle Axiome, though it have a large extent in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Arguments which may be diſpoſed in it, yet (if but the <hi>Crypſis,</hi> and oblique predications be declared by
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170289:25"/> an apt explication) it is eaſie to be judged of, as for the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Doctrine, by reaſon of the direct union of the parts: whether it be only one axiome, or doe contain ſeveral ones in it: unleſſe it be when there is ſome compoſition either in the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, or in the conſequent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the antecedent be of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulate parts (ſo that the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent be enunciated only, one of all united together, not of the ſingle ones ſeverally, for otherwiſe it is an axiome of a copulate judgement) and that they require a ſeveral tractation, they may be propoſed ſeverally in ſo many axiomes, (with a reſpect to the conſequent, (<hi>viz.</hi> in good, as requiſite thereunto; in evill, as tending to it) and afterwards the conſequent of all taken together may be laid open.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170289:25"/> As for example, <hi>Bleſſed are they which hear the Word of God and keep it.</hi> 1. <hi>For a bleſſing, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that we hear the Word of God.</hi> 2. <hi>That we keep it.</hi> 3. <hi>Thoſe who doe both theſe things are bleſſed.</hi> See the like in a large compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Sect. 5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Likewiſe if there be a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation in the conſequent (ſo that the copulated parts may be ſpoken of the antecedent, not ſeverally, but taken toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) the judgement is the ſame of it, as was of the other. See an example, Chap. 6. Sect. 3. out of Mat. 17.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Propoſitions which they call Modal, (if we meet with them in Scripture, in the ſame ſenſe as Logicians take them) may be referred to a ſingle axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome. And in theſe the <hi>modus</hi> doth conſtitute the conſequent,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170289:26"/> the ſubſtance of the axiome being contracted into the antecedent. Theſe <hi>modi</hi> are nothing, but the affections of the axiome <hi>ingenere</hi> (which as true, is either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent, or neceſſary; as falſe, either poſſible, or impoſſible) and are to be underſtood by the affection, and manner of diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the arguments.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Although where word the <hi>Eſt</hi> is meerly Syncategoremati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and both parts, or the one in reſpect of the other, implyes a negation to the real <hi>eſſe</hi> (as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feigned, ſome privative, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicing things) there neither part with <hi>Eſt</hi> categorematically taken, will make a divine axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome; and though when by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the nature of the parts, and affection of the one with the other, an axiome may be conſtituted; it ſeems to be there
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170289:26"/> contained rather by deduction, then expreſſely. Yet if the thing will ſo bear it, and the unſold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and treating of that axiome by way of uſe be not ſufficient, but the reſpect which that noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath to ſome other part in the Text, or ſome other juſt cauſe require, that it may ſome way be treated of ſeverally; It may be ſometimes propoſed, (yet but ſeldom) and followed as far as need ſhall require, either in the whole part, or in a particle of the part. Pſal. 1. The conſequent <hi>Bleſt</hi> is ſpoken of the antecedent, which conſiſts of ſeveral parts, in either of which parts there is a copulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the firſt a trebble <hi>climax.</hi> That axiome may (unleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure the word <hi>pius</hi> may be ſuppleted for an Antecedent out of the Antitheſis of the 4. verſe)
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170289:27"/> be handled according to the rule laid down in the ſecond ſection of this chapter; Firſt, the former part of the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, then the latter, and laſtly the conſequent is to be applyed to them, as conjunct. Every part of the former, and firſt that which is abſolute, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with the conſequent. As for example, <hi>The wicked have their counſell: It is required, for to be bleſt, not to walk in their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. The ſinners have their way; It is required for to be bleſt, to not ſtand in their way. The ſcornful have their ſeat: It is required for to be bleſt, to not ſit in their ſeat.</hi> Then the Copulation: <hi>It is required, if we will be bleſſed, that we neither walk in the counſell of the wicked, nor ſtand, &amp;c. nor ſit, &amp;c.</hi> Out of this axiome the <hi>climax</hi> or gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation may be obſerved by way
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170289:27"/> of uſe. And if this way of treaty be not ſufficient, we may proceed further in this manner, There are wicked, there are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, there are ſcorners. There are both thoſe, and theſe. And ſo in the other two; but ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractly, that ſolid axiomes may not be anteverted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. Of a Compoſite Axiome.</head>
               <p>ALthough in a Compoſite Axiome the unitive force of the parts for the moſt part ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate it ſelf in a Grammatical conjunction: yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeeing Grammatical con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions are taken looſely, and in a various ſenſe, as well in the Original languages in which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170289:28"/> Scripture was written, as in thoſe into which they were tranſlated, we muſt not ſtick too much to theſe ſymboles or por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but we muſt firſt look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the affections of arguments which are there diſpoſed, and the rule of judging every axiom.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the parts of the Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite doe contain ſomewhat in them which is abſolute, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſee Chap. 4. Sect. 6) and they require a diſtinct treaty (which a Connex preciſely taken, and a Disjunct doe not admit) that which is abſolute in the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, may ſometimes be reſerved untill we come at it, as Joh. 8.18. The antecedent. <hi>I am one that bear witneſſe of my ſelf.</hi> The ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute in the conſequent. <hi>The Father ſent me.</hi> The conſequent. <hi>The Father that ſent me, beareth witneſs of me.</hi> The Conjuncts. <hi>Both I
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170289:28"/> and the Father, &amp;c.</hi> See ch. 7. Sect. 1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Excluſive axiomes (which we meet with oftentimes in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture differ little or nothing one from the other) although they have the face of ſingle ones, yet becauſe they doe alwayes indeed imply a compoſition, if they be ſully to be treated of, they muſt be referred to a compoſite axiom. But they reſolve themſelves into two axioms, whereof one ought to be enunciated affirmatively, the other negatively. And as the affirmation is before the negation, ſo that which is enunciated af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatively, requires the firſt place in the treating. The Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive in the antecedent. 2 Tim. 4.11. <hi>Alone</hi> (or <hi>only</hi>) <hi>Luke is with me,</hi> as if he ſaid; And <hi>Luke is with me; and other of the Diſciples are not with me.</hi> In the conſequent. Matth. 4.10. <hi>Him only ſhalt thou
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170289:29"/> ſerve,</hi> that is to ſay, and <hi>Him ſhalt thou worſhip,</hi> and <hi>another thou ſhalt not.</hi> In the ſame ſenſe might be ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſerve none but him.</hi> The Exceptive in the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent. Act. 8.1. <hi>They were all feattered abroad, &amp;c. Except the Apoſtles, the reſt were diſperſed. The Apoſtles were not diſperſed.</hi> In the Conſequent. Matth. 17.21. <hi>This kind goeth not out but by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and faſting.</hi> 1. <hi>It goeth out by prayer and faſting.</hi> 2. Other ways, <hi>It doth not go out.</hi> The firſt axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome is to be treated of accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the rule, Chap. 5. Sect. 3. <hi>Prayer is required to have this go out.</hi> 2. <hi>Faſting is required.</hi> 3. <hi>Byboth it go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out.</hi> Sometimes for greater evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences ſake the affirmative, &amp; the negative are both expreſſed: As in the Exceptive, Deut. 4.35. <hi>The Lord he is God,</hi> and <hi>there is none elſe but him.</hi> The ſame is ſignified in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170289:29"/> the Excluſives, by gemination of the ſubject <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. (which the Septuagint doe often render by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>only,</hi> as 2 Sam. 17.2. 1 King. 8.39, &amp;c.) Sometimes the Excluſive is ſet together with the Exceptive, as 2 King. 17,18, &amp;c. ſo Luk. 5.21, &amp;c. In the affirmate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive, the note addes the negate; in the negate, by a double negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the affirmate. In the exceptive affirmate, the note layes the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate; in the negate the affirmate.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Comparates although they be many times diſpoſed in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle axiome, yet becauſe they can ſcarſe be treated of ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, unleſſe they may be more fully diſtinguiſhed by parts, and ſo be referred (whereunto full comparations belong) to the compoſite axiome, of theſe we muſt give ſome premonition in this place.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170289:30"/>
               <p n="5">5. Where every comparation is ſaid to be either in the
<list>
                     <item>quantity</item>
                     <item>quality.</item>
                  </list> You muſt note that theſe terms are taken at large, and Logical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p n="6">6. When the quantity or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is ſaid to be a conjunction, or to contain the unitive force of the parts; it is underſtood notwithſtanding to ſuperadde alſo its peculiar force of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the nature of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Note of Comparation which is added to Reddition is chief, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Aliquid</hi> is chief in the Axiome, and for whoſe ſake the argument is added.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Alſo the Grammatical notes of Comparates ſometimes doe not diſtinguiſh one <hi>ſpecies</hi> or kind from the other. See an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, Ch. 7. Sect. 9. Sometimes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170289:30"/> they are not ſet by it, Chap. 7. Sect. 4. &amp; 7.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Comparative degree doth not alwayes argue a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in either, but a leſſer par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the oppoſite, as Ezek. 16 52. Lam. 4.9. See an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, Chap. 7. Sect. 4.</p>
               <p n="10">10. In the treaty of Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates (whither the quantity, or quality be expreſſed in the Text, or no) it will be uſeful ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, to premiſe or adde to thoſe reſpects wherein they doe agree (as in Equals, and Sembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles) thoſe wherein they do not agree. And premiſe or adde thoſe in which they doe not agree (as Unequals, and Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blables) to thoſe in which they doe agree. Eſpecially in ſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles this is to be obſerved, that they be not extended beyond their ſcope: which is done often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170289:31"/> and dangerouſly. So both the comparation ſhall be illuſtrated, and the detortion or wreſting to an evill ſenſe ſhall be avoided.</p>
               <p n="11">11. If the comparation be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, as concerning the reſpect in which it is inſtituted or ſet, either by the Text, or by the Context (though peradventure in other places other reſpects be manifeſted) let that only be treated of, and the reſt reſerved for their proper places, ſeeing it is ſufficient to ſatisfie the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the preſent Text.</p>
               <p n="12">12. If it be unlimited, and divers reſpects and profits of the Homogeneal may be brought, (becauſe Scripture is to be taken in latitude, if it be not reſtrained neither by the Context, nor the Analogy of faith or truth) they may well be brought.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170289:31"/>
               <p n="13">13. The reſpect in an illimit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed compariſon (whether it be one, or manifold) it muſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with an Explication out of the habitude of an argument to the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Aliquid:</hi> and ſo the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine be conſtituted, one out of one, more out of more. Where the reſpect, as being founded upon an Argument (which is more known and plain to the hearers) is to be known and plain, as applyed to the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Aliquid</hi> certain, and of a firm truth, for from hence depend the uſe and efficacy of the Doctrine. Gen. 15.1. <hi>I am thy ſhield.</hi> Axiome. <hi>As a ſhield protects a man who makes a right uſe of it, ſo God doth faithful Abraham.</hi> Here <hi>protection</hi> is the reſpect; known by the uſe of the ſhield, certain by the authority of the divine promiſe, Gen. 12.2,3. For the further Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170289:32"/> of the axiome, the reſpects, wherein the comparates differ, may be ſhewn. The ſhield is the inſtrumental cauſe of the protection; God, at leaſt, the principal. A ſhield defends from an enemy which aſſaults one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; God is a ſhield <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>round about his people,</hi> Pſal. 125.2. A ſhield is not alway es at hand: But God round about his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth even for ever,</hi> ibid. A ſhield is a defence againſt a corporal enemy only, not againſt a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual. God againſt all.</p>
               <p n="14">14. But there is no place of invention, which lies more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to wreſting, to infer extream bad ſenſes, then this of Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, and eſpecially of ſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: none doth more eaſily draw the petty people (and I pray God not many of their
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170289:32"/> leaders alſo) into the pit, none uſes to be more frequently uſed either to oppreſſe truth, or eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh errours. Therefore here ought to be a great deal of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eſpecially in aſſigning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of an illimited compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I could wiſh this one law might be obſerved, as that of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> that at leaſt the Reddition (in which <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Aliquid</hi> is contained) ſhould be proved ſolidly, out of manifeſt places of holy Scripture. There is need of the ſame caution in thoſe places is ſet down con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſedly, and the Propoſition is explicated in ſeveral parts: as in many Evangelical Parables: and alſo where no reddition is ſet down. That Propoſition, Exod. 12.46. did ſeem to want a Reddition, untill the event, and the Apoſtle ſhould declare
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170289:33"/> it, Joh. 19.36. So that of Hoſ. 11.1. If Divines would care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully uſe this caution alſo to compariſons which they bring in matters of great moment to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards faith, or manners, we ſhould have more celeſtiall food, and leſſe ſtrife.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Comparates in quantity doe argue more preſſingly and diſtinctly then thoſe which are in quality.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Feigned Comparates if they be diſpoſed in a Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite which requires the truth of parts, doe not fall under this rule of judgement; ſee Ch. 3. Sect. 1. Yet ſome diſtinction may be uſed in feigned ones. For ſome are meerly feigned; ſome are taken out of the common uſe; which though they do not touch any ſingular hiſtory, neither are they determined to here and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170289:33"/> now, yet they contain an indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite truth in them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if need be, there may be axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes made of them, to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with reſtriction, and briefly run over. Luk. 18. <hi>There is ſometimes a Judge in a</hi> City, which neither feareth God, nor regardeth man. Sometimes a widow is wronged by her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary. Being wronged ſhe uſeth to complain to, and be impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate with the judge. The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt judge will ſometimes doe juſtice to the widow, to avoid the trouble o of importunity.</p>
               <p n="17">17. If a comparation be met with <hi>obiter,</hi> or by the way, and not principally in ſome ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; it may be more ſlightly treated, and ſubordinately to principal axiomes, as Rom. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Wherefore ye muſt needs be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, &amp;c.</hi> In this Text the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170289:34"/> is <hi>ſubjection</hi> (whoſe ſubject with generality and object of the perſon, you muſt ſupply out of the firſt verſe of the ſame chapter) is diſpoſed with an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned <hi>neceſſity,</hi> which is argued from two cauſes comparate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween themſelves in an unequal quantity (<hi>not onely, but alſo</hi>) axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes to be treated in the Text. 1. Every ſoul ought neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>to be ſubject to a ſupereminent power.</hi> 2. <hi>For wrath it is neceſſary to be ſubject.</hi> 3. <hi>For conſcience, &amp;c.</hi> 4. <hi>More for conſcience then for wrath.</hi> (5. Out of the relative conſideration in the illative or inferring note <hi>Wherefore,</hi> which joyns theſe words with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent) <hi>for a ſuper eminent power, is a revenger of wrath, and a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God, and that for the good of all,</hi> therefore to be ſubject, &amp;c. <hi>is neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170289:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. Of a Copulate Axiome.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>SEeing a Copulate Axiome conſiſts as it were of colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral parts, ſo that one does not depend of the other, the truth of each one in it ſelf is required, and by the copulation of them it is ſo, that if one be falſe, the whole axiome is judged to be falſe. Hence it comes that the parts may be ſeverally propoſed as Doctrines; then as united. See an example of an affirmed copulate, of affirmed parts, Ch. 6. Sect. 2. Of denyed. Mat. 23.13. <hi>Ye goe not in.</hi> 2. You ſuffer not, &amp;c. 3. <hi>Ye neither goe in, nor ſuffer;</hi> of one affirmed, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther denyed. Prov. 10.22. 1. <hi>The
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170289:35"/> bleſſing of the Lord it maketh rich.</hi> 2. <hi>He addeth no ſorrow with it.</hi> 3. It doth both make rich, and <hi>doth not adde, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Moſt comparates ought to be referred to this axiome, ſo they be taken declaratively, where the ſentence is not ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, or an illation or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of one comparate is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended out of the other. To the comparates in quantity doe alſo belong the relations of the place, and time, by the ſame law. An example of like, or equals, a Cor. 11.22. <hi>Are they Hebrews? ſo am I, &amp;c. And I no leſſe then they,</hi> or <hi>as well as they.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. When out of the Text, and Context appears to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a comparation of peeres or equals, though it be expreſſed under the ſpecies of a connex of impoſſible parts, yet it will be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170289:35"/> of a copulate judgement, and the contradictories of the falſe parts will conſtitute the parts of the comparation, Jer. 31.36,37. God doth before, and after theſe verſes, expreſſe the firmneſſe of his Covenant with <hi>Abrahams</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; and doth ſuſpend the contrary by the impoſſible ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in theſe two verſes. The Axiomes therefore, verſ. 36. are, <hi>Theſe Ordinances ſhall not depart from before me; The ſeed of Iſrael ſhall not ceaſe, &amp;c. No more this, then that,</hi> ſo verſ. 37. The Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent. <hi>The heavent cannot be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured above, or the earth ſearched out beneath;</hi> (namely by men.) In the Conſequent. 1. The Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <hi>They have done many evils.</hi> 2. I will not caſt off all the ſeed <hi>of Iſcael.</hi> 3. <hi>Not for all theſe things which they have done,</hi> (or becauſe a diſcretion or a diviſion is to be
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170289:36"/> underſtood) <hi>though they have done many evils, yet will I not caſt off all, &amp;c.</hi> Laſtly, out of the united parts. <hi>No more the one, then the other.</hi> Thoſe which are une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual doe likewiſe belong hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Prov. 17.12. <hi>Let a Bear rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of her whelps meet a man, &amp;c.</hi> 1. <hi>It is evill to have a Bear robbed of her whelps to meet a man.</hi> 2. <hi>It is evill to have a fool in his folly to meet a man.</hi> 3. <hi>This is a greater evill then the other.</hi> In the third axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome is to be explained the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of evill in this, more then in the other, 2 Pet. 2.21. <hi>It had been better for them not to have known the way of righteouſneſſe, then after they have known it, to turn from the holy Commandement, &amp;c.</hi> 1. <hi>Gods Commandement is holy.</hi> 2. <hi>An holy Commandement is the way of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi> 3. <hi>To have an holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement delivered unto him; is to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170289:36"/> know the way of righteouſneſſe.</hi> Theſe three axiomes doe not belong to the expreſſing of the comparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Of the firſt, ſee the rule, Ch. 4. Sect. 6. and of the two latter, Chap. 4. Sect. 14. But the parts of the comparation are, 1. <hi>Not to have known the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> or <hi>the holy commandement had been evill for them.</hi> 2. <hi>To turn from the known way, or from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment given, is evill.</hi> 3. <hi>The latter is a leſſer evill then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Semblables. Where a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity is intended, but it hath not ſeemed good to argue it diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſometimes we paſſe over into a ſimilitude, and the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the quantity is expreſſed, as Gen. 15.5. The innumerabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. <hi>And he brought him forth, and ſaid, Look now towards heaven, &amp;c.</hi> Where the Protaſis, <hi>the ſtars are
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170289:37"/> not to be numbered,</hi> is proved by the condeſcent to the manner of humane witneſſe through expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. <hi>Look upon, and number if thou canſt,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>when thou haſt tryed thou canſt not.</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſis. Thy ſeed ſhall be innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable. The note of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſuperadding the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to the copulation, <hi>So ſhall, &amp;c.</hi> is proved by Divine teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, <hi>The Lord ſaith.</hi> Axiomes. 1. <hi>Thou canſt not number the ſtars.</hi> 2. <hi>I call to witneſſe thine own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</hi> 3. <hi>Thy Seed ſhall not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be numbred.</hi> 4. <hi>As not the stars, ſo neither thy ſeed.</hi> (The reſpect in the quality, <hi>So:</hi> that is to ſay, 1. <hi>By reaſon of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> 2. <hi>Conſpicuouſly.</hi> 3. <hi>To men that have skill and experience in numbring it ſhall be innumerable as the ſtars are to now thee</hi>) 5. <hi>The Lord ſaith it ſhall be ſo.</hi> 6. <hi>God brought
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170289:37"/> forth Abraham.</hi> 7. <hi>He ſaid, &amp;c.</hi> 8. <hi>After he had promiſed him an heir out of his own bowels, he brought him forth and ſaid, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Mat. 13.45,46. <hi>The Kingdom of heaven is like, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe words contain a Reddition, but ſet down confuſedly: the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent a Propoſition diſtinctly explicated, in a Merchant, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his object and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And though the reddition be joyned with one only argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Propoſition (where it is ſaid <hi>like unto a Merchant</hi>) yet it is to be underſtood, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the whole propoſition, and vertually to involve the ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logal parts, to its parts. So verſ. 24. <hi>The Kingdom of heaven is likened unto a man who ſowed good ſeed in his ground.</hi> Where by our Saviours own interpretation, He himſelf is the ſower, and to the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170289:38"/> reſt of the parts are applyed thoſe things which are in the Kingdom (though not all of the Kingdom). Only to the zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſervants he applyes nothing. as if he would not have ſuch Miniſters named under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel as ſtudy or endeavour the killing of Hereſie. <hi>Caſtellio</hi> doth rightly warn us upon Matth. 11.16. <hi>The whole matter, not one word only is compared as in other parables.</hi> Out of this Protaſis if need were there might axiomes be framed. Namely, <hi>That Merchants doe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively ſeek after things of this world; that their induſtry ſometimes proves good to them, finding things of great valew. For the moſt part they are cunning enough, ſelling all they have for a greater gain, buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which will bring them the greateſt commodiouſneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Of theſe things, ſee Chap. 6. Sect. 16.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170289:38"/> Proper axiomes of the Text. <hi>As the Merchant which ſeeks for pearls, ſo <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, thoſe who are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in the Goſpel, doe ſeek for ſolid good things. As a Merchant which findes a Pearl of great value, ſo theſe by ſeeking doe find life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. As he ſels all that he hath to buy that Pearl: ſo they deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to obtain this. As he buyes that, ſo they by obſerving the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the Evangelical Covenant, to which the promiſe is annexed</hi> (<hi>God for Chriſts ſake</hi> having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion) obtain this.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Diſſemblables alſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a note (as there are many in <hi>Solomons Proverbs,</hi> and elſewhere) doe ſeem to belong hereunto. Tranſlators ſometimes in theſe doe render an Hebrew [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] by a copulative; oſtentimes by [<hi>ſed,</hi> but] as it were to ſhew the diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude. But they are well
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170289:39"/> copulated ſo far as either Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blable is enunciated with its quality; for herein they agree, that either hath its quality diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with it, Prov. 14.29. <hi>He that is ſlow to wrath, is of great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, but he that is haſty of ſpirit exalteth folly.</hi> Where ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule, Ch. 4. Sect. 13. ſomething may be added, out of either part, unto the other: and ſo the parts are fully un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded, <hi>He that is ſlow to wrath is of great underſtanding, and exalts it: He that is haſty of ſpirit is great in folly, and exalts it.</hi> Theſe being treated of, let the Colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Diſſemblables ſucceed. To the unfolding of which, may be propoſed, in what they doe agree, according to the rule, Chap. 6. Sect. 10. <hi>Each one is great in his quality. Each one hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which he exalts.</hi> But the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170289:39"/> quality is very divers, to which alſo thoſe things add a weight in which they both agree.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. In an affirmed copulate, and which contains a diſcretion, or ſeparation of [<hi>non,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſed</hi>] namely [of <hi>not</hi> &amp; <hi>but</hi>] there ſeems to be a full enunciation, Pſal. 1. <hi>And the godly man ſhall proſper like a tree; And the ungodly man not ſo, but is unhappy as the chaffe, &amp;c.</hi> Where either Diſſemblable, is argued from the Semblable, for the greater illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the diſſimilitude. See examples of Diſſemblables ſully diſpoſed, Joh. 3.36. &amp; 4.13,14. where in the firſt part there is a Protaſis, in the ſecond an Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podoſis in the
<list>
                        <item>Negation of the like, or Semblable quality.</item>
                        <item>Various poſition of the quality.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. Heb. 12.24. [<hi>Better</hi>] though
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170289:40"/> it be ſpoken very largely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the manifold reaſon of the good, yet it ſeems it cannot bee here expounded of unequall, but diſſemblable, [—<hi>the bloud of ſprinkling ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth better things then that of</hi> Abel] <hi>Better things,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>other</hi> or <hi>otherwiſe;</hi> Namely, <hi>the bloud of ſprinkling ſpeaks better things. The bloud of</hi> Abel <hi>not good things,</hi> ſee Chap. 4. Sect. 8. It may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by the Protaſis (for it is an illimited comparation) out of the Hiſtory, Gen. 4.</p>
                  <p>The bloud of <hi>Abel</hi> did ſpeak
<list>
                        <item>towards God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.</item>
                        <item>to <hi>Cain</hi> horrour</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Out of the Antapodoſis out of the Apoſtle the bloud of Chriſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170289:40"/> ſpeaks
<list>
                        <item>towards God propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
                        <item>to the hearts of belet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkled with it, peace.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the further explication, the reſpects may be brought, in which they agree (according to the rule, Chap. 6. Sect. 10.) 1. <hi>The Floud of either was unjuſtly ſpilt.</hi> 2. <hi>The bloud of either ſpeaks.</hi> The ſeparate treating of the parts, may be here omitted, as not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expreſſed in the Text. And where they are expreſſed, they may be fully treated: but here ſufficiently in the collation or comparation. The Axiomes in the collation. 1. <hi>And the bloud of</hi> Abel <hi>of it ſelf ſpeaks vengeance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; and far otherwiſe the bloud of Chriſt, ſpeaks propitiation made towards God for all.</hi> 2. <hi>The
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170289:41"/> bloud of</hi> Abel <hi>ſpeaks horror to</hi> Cain. <hi>But that of Chriſt peace to all thoſe who by faith have their hearts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkled therewith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Negate Copulate.</head>
                  <p n="10">10. Thoſe Comparates whoſe note is the negation of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite ſpecies or kind might ſeem to be diſpoſed in the Negate Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulate. And the note indeed doth ſhew that there are ſuch argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; yet they are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ully and diſtinctly enunciated in that axiome. For the Negation that notes beſt, doth terminate it ſelf in the indication of the gender, and rejection of the oppoſite ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: whence followeth that the other is diſpoſed there, but in a confuſed conception. Neither is the note alwayes certain: as a negation of the greater doth
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170289:41"/> not infer a known parity or equality, Joh. 4.12. &amp; 8.53. &amp; 13.16.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Diſſemblables by negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſimilitude (although they be fully diſtinguiſhed) cannot be fully comprehended in this denyed, or Negate copulate. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe beſides the negation of the proportion between Semblables, is required a poſition of a divers quality.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. A Copulate is more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly denyed, as for the parts, when the bond or connexion is abſolutely denyed, neither ſeems it (except ſuch as are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute) to contain any more axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes then it ſelf: unleſſe we think, they be ſometimes to be pointed at, becauſe of the ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers prudency. As [<hi>you cannot ſerve both God and Mammon</hi>] <hi>you may ſerve him, and you may ſerve
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170289:42"/> this, you cannot ſerve both together,</hi> ſee Chap. 8. Sect. 9.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. A Copulate which is falſe on the one part, is more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denyed, as to the parts, by the Diſcrete; for ſo it is diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed which part is true, and which falſe.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. A Copulate of both parts, affirmed and falſe, is conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denyed, taking away the parts by the copulate of the denyed parts, Act. 25.8. A Copulate of both parts denyed and falſe, contrary wiſe: Iſa. 47.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="cryptic">
                  <head>Crypſis of the Copulate.</head>
                  <p>Seeing that a Copulate of its own nature doth not ſeem to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a neceſſary union of the parts; and doth not alwayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſomewhat (at leaſt of any great moment) as reſulting out
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170289:42"/> of their union; therefore in ſuch, the axiome which ariſeth out of the copulation may be omitted. Otherwiſe that axiome is of great moment, by reaſon of the authority, by which the parts are united, and the neceſſity of it, to that which it directly looks upon in that union.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Becauſe in the Copulate there be Collateral parts, if there be little or no difference between them, unleſſe it be in words, the conſequents of the parts may be joyned into one: And likewiſe the antecedents. Prov. 31.30. <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and beauty deceitful and vain.</hi> Finally, if ſuch parts be any more illuſtrated in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, they may likewiſe be joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together. Pſal. 51.2. <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>My ſin, mine iniquity.</hi> 2. <hi>He deſires to be waſhed and cleanſed from them.</hi> 3. <hi>He deſires to be waſhed
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170289:43"/> throughly.</hi> 4. <hi>All this he deſires of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="17">17. In a comparation, a ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral treating of the Propoſition may oftentimes be omitted, or at leaſt be ſhortly knit up, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be feigned to an hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſimilitude, or true. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it often conſiſts of a matter which is but little Theological. 2. It is not primarily intended in the Text, but the whole or chief uſe of it is in the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Reddition, and the illuſtration of it. 3. It is more known and clear to the hearers, who by it are to be taught the Reddition. 4. In the reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Doctrine, it comes firſt to be inculcated or preſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mind or heart of the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by uſes. And here the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er might take upon him that of our Saviour, Hear what the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170289:43"/> unjuſt Judge ſaith, Luk. 18.6. And being to exhort to ſedulity and care in ſeeking out the <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> or <hi>chief good,</hi> out of the parable of the Merchant; attend unto his care in worldly things. <hi>The careful Merchant runs to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt parts of the Indies, &amp;c.</hi> So the ſeveral tractation of the Reddition may oftentimes be omitted; namely, when it ſhall be ſufficiently treated of, with the note of comparation, or in the collation it ſelf of the parts. And ſo very many Texts of full comparations may be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently exhauſted, if the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition be applyed to the Redditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (or as the reaſon of it ſhall require) the part to the part: and ſo the Doctrine be conſtituted.</p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:170289:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170289:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170289:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. Of the Connex.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p n="1">1. HEre the affirmation ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, that if there be an antecedent, there is alſo a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent. So that though there be no note, or that which is, is alien, or not pertinent (as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentime it is uſual) yet if the illation of the conſequent from the antecedent be intended, the axiome ought to be thought belong to this place. The truth thereof conſiſts in the true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of the parts, that either out of one, or both falſe ones, the abſolutely true may be; as alſo out of the true ones, the falſe; namely, when the one doth not follow out of the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170289:45"/> other. Hence, by reaſon of the form of this axiome preciſely looked upon, the Doctrine can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be conſtituted out of either part, though the parts ſeverally conſidered were true; becauſe the falſe ones alſo may conſiſt with the truth of the axiom. Yet abſolute axiomes may be in the parts. In the Antecedent, Gal. 1.8. the abſolute is, <hi>Hath been preached unto you.</hi> In the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, Joh. 8.55. the Abſolute, <hi>You are lyars.</hi> An example of a <hi>Connex,</hi> where a like is inferred from a like, 2 Sam. 15.21. <hi>As the Lord liveth, and my Lord the King liveth:</hi> But <hi>in what place</hi> [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] <hi>my Lord the King ſhall be, even there alſo will thy ſervant be.</hi> It ſeems to be a prerupt, or haſty ſpeech of a Souldier haſtening to expreſſe his faith; as if he did ſay, <hi>I will
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170289:46"/> not return unto</hi> Abſalom <hi>as thou wiſheſt me, But in what place, &amp;c.</hi> The Comparation is limited to two reſpects in the Text, which being incompatible are propoſed disjunctly. Whether in death; there <hi>alſo,</hi> &amp;c. The place in which, or the condition <hi>David</hi> ſhould be in either to life or death, it infers <hi>Ittai</hi> would in be the ſame, or the like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Axiomes. 1. <hi>Ittai profeſſeth the King to be his Lord, and himſelf to be his ſervant.</hi> 2. <hi>If my Lord the King be in death, there will his ſervant be with him.</hi> 3. <hi>If in life, he will be there with him.</hi> 4. <hi>In whether condition ſoever the King ſhall be, in the ſame alſo ſhall he be.</hi> The antecedent doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr the conſequent, taking its force in that <hi>Ittai</hi> confirms it with an oath, that whatſoever the Kings condition ſhould be, the ſame ſhould be his: whoſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170289:46"/> efficacy is perceived by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this manner of teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Yet this belongs unto the Connex (where there is relation of the conſequence) that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the truth of the parts alſo. And therefore it offers the axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes to be treated of diſtinctly in their parts, then that which reſults out of their union. But how much the more it declines from the bare connexion, ſo much the nearer it comes to the nature of a Syllogiſm, ſo that the cauſal conjunction being taken away, it uſually reſolves it ſelf into an Enthymema. And alſo a whole Syllogiſme may be comprehended in this axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Hereunto belong the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall (alſo when the cauſe by accident inferres the effect, as
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170289:47"/> Eccleſ. 8.11.) and rational notes, if they doe truely note (which they doe not alwayes doe, as John 19. ver. 4, 5, 6, 23, &amp;c.) and which ſoever have the ſame force or efficacy: whereof the former belong to the Antecedent, the latter to the conſequent. In both of them the antecedent al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes contains the cauſe of the conſequence, and ſometimes of the conſequent. The Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Crypſis or tranſpoſition of parts is very frequent in this axiome. <hi>Si, if,</hi> is oftentimes ſet down for [<hi>cùm, ſeeing that,</hi> or <hi>quandoquidem, ſeeing that</hi>] Luk. 11.13. Joh. 10.35. &amp; 13.14, &amp;c. Oftentimes the cauſall note is wanting, as Pſal. 25.8. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is ſet down for the illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or inferring, as Pſal. 116.10. Sometimes the illative is wanting, as Pſal. 116.1. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170289:47"/> both, as Pſal. 118.6. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is tacitely contained in the antecedent participle, as 2 Cor. 7.1. Eſpecially where the participle ſignifies notice: as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Beholding,</hi> Acts 4.14. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſeeing,</hi> Col. 4.1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>when they heard,</hi> Acts 7.54. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>knowing,</hi> Heb. 10.34. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>remembring,</hi> Act. 20.31. Sometimes it is found with an alien note, as Matth. 3.14. <hi>I have need to be baptized of thee, and comeſt thou to me?</hi> as if he ſaid, <hi>Seeing I have need to be baptized of thee, I doe not ſee why</hi> (or ſome ſuch like thing) <hi>thou ſhouldeſt come to me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Oftentimes the antecedent of this connex containeth that which preceded, ſometimes vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, and ſometimes formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Therefore if there it have been treated of by the Preacher,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170289:48"/> and here it be vertually recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to infer the conſequent; it ought here to be freely treated of, and only according to what is ſuperadded by the manner of recollection, 2 Cor. 7.1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Having therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo chap. 4. verſ. 1. In both places the demonſtrative, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically ſet down, ſeemes to note an excellency; in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, of the foreſaid promiſes, in the latter of the foreſaid Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration. But if formally; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the conſequent, and the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of it out of the antecedent offer themſelves: for the repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the antecedent, as lately treated of, will ſuffice. Rom. 8.17. <hi>And if children</hi> (where <hi>Si, if,</hi> ſtands for <hi>cum, ſeeing that</hi>) <hi>then heirs.</hi> 1. <hi>True believers</hi> (whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription was before) <hi>are heirs.</hi> 2. <hi>Becauſe children are heirs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170289:48"/>
                  <p n="5">5. An axiome out of a finall cauſe (where the <hi>finis,</hi> or end, under its note <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>finally</hi> taken, or its equipollent, is ſet to infer the <hi>medium</hi> or means) may alſo be referred to this place. Which kind of axiome (becauſe it is frequently obvious in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture) we will here ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of concerning its illative, or inferring force. One that acts according to reaſon, looks upon the end under the reaſon of conveniency; He wiſheth, or with a kind of willity deſires. This deſire excites him to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, whether there be any means, by which it may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. The poſſibility found out, and added to the end ſomewhat increaſes this deſire. So increaſed, it excites him again to ſeek out the nature of the means. 1. Whether they be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170289:49"/> poſſible to be applyed by this agent of himſelf, or ſome way elſe. For want of this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the deſire vaniſheth into deſpair. 2. Whether they be not of ſuch weight, but that the end may abundantly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe it. 3. Whether they be neceſſary, ſo that the end cannot be obtained without them: or at leaſt as neceſſary as others, if there be ſeveral wayes to that end. 4. Whether they be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſo that by the uſe of theſe, the end cannot chuſe but be attained; or at leaſt probable. For defect of theſe three, the deſire vaniſhes into a neglect. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire occupyed about ſuch an end and the means, and by faith ſtrengthened about them, grows into hope or efficacious deſire of the end. And becauſe the means are firſt by nature, as far
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170289:49"/> as to the actual being, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductives of the actual end, or the fruition; therefore the agent puts the means into an actual <hi>eſſe</hi> or being, making uſe of them, to attain the end. The end being thus ſpecified, is truly the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in operable things, as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the compleat <hi>volition</hi> or <hi>will</hi> of it ſelf, and of the means to it. And all theſe things are eminently found, as well in the excellency of the end, as in the habitude of the means unto it in the Covenant between
<list>
                        <item>Chriſt and the Father.</item>
                        <item>Us, and God in Chriſt.</item>
                     </list> Which two Covenants (whereof the firſt is the foundation of the other) doe afford very many axiomes of this kind in the Scripture.</p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170289:50"/>
                  <p n="6">6. In this axiome, for the moſt part the <hi>Medium</hi> or means is diſpoſed in the firſt place, and then the end. Yet if the end hath the reaſon of the argument inferring the <hi>medium,</hi> the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent of the axiome contains the end, and the conſequent the <hi>medium,</hi> or means. But becauſe the means may abſolutely be looked upon, before it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as determinated to this end; it may conveniently be treated of in that order as it is placed (unleſſe by chance the reaſon of ſome ſpecial text be againſt it) ſo it be abſtractly in this abſolute nature, reſerving the reſpect to the end of the Doctrine, which is to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed out of the united parts, Luk. 19.10. <hi>The Son of man is come to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt,</hi> where the coming of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170289:50"/> the Son of man is argued from a double end, copulately diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed: Subordinate, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal: <hi>Who,</hi> from the object. <hi>What,</hi> from the adjunct. The parts, the antecedent, <hi>to ſeek and ſave,</hi> (or <hi>becauſe be intended to ſeek and to ſave.</hi>) The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, <hi>Therefore he came.</hi> The axiome, (the explication being premiſed) <hi>We were loſt.</hi> 2. <hi>The Son of man came.</hi> 3. <hi>He intended to ſeek.</hi> 4. <hi>To ſave that which was loſt.</hi> 5. <hi>To ſeek and to ſave.</hi> 6. <hi>Becauſe he would ſeek and ſave, therefore he came.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. For there are alſo many places in Scripture in which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the note, is contained the event of the finall cauſe: And theſe axiomes doe alſo belong hereunto, the adjunct to it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing connexed, but in a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry order of parts. For the event
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170289:51"/> which lyes hidden under this note, conſtitutes the conſequent part of the axiome. Of this kind ſeeme to be thoſe ſayings [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] <hi>that the Scripture might be fulfilled, er accompliſhed.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, <hi>When theſe things were done, the Scripture was fulfilled, which had foretold it ſhould be,</hi> or <hi>theſe things were done, to the end that the Scripture might be fulfilled,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>that</hi> pro <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>to the end.</hi> An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Matth. 2.15. <hi>Becauſe he was in</hi> Egypt, <hi>&amp;c. was fulfilled the ſaying of the Lord by the Prophet,</hi> (namely in the Antitype, or red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) Hoſ. 11.1. The axiomes of the antecedent. Herod <hi>dyed,</hi> Joſeph <hi>with the child and his Mother was in</hi> Egypt <hi>ſo long,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>till the death of</hi> Herod. In the conſequent. <hi>As God called
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170289:51"/> his Son, namely,</hi> Iſrael: <hi>ſo he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his only begotten Son out of</hi> Egypt. <hi>This was ſpoken by the Prophet. From the Lord by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. It is fulfilled. Becauſe he was in</hi> Egypt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (and being warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, be returned) <hi>therefore it was fulfilled.</hi> And in this ſenſe ſeemes to be expounded [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] <hi>that it might be fulfilled</hi> by [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] <hi>then was fulfilled,</hi> v. 17. <hi>Becauſe there was a great cry for the death of the</hi> Bethleemitiſh <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the ſaying of</hi> Jeremy, (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the like) <hi>was fulfilled,</hi> ſo Mark. 15.28. <hi>And the Scripture was fulfilled, which ſaith, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. Sometimes under the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the finall cauſe, is ſet down the event meerly by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent alſo in a contrary order of parts, Matth. 10.34. <hi>I came to ſend a ſword.</hi> Having premiſed a due explication, the ſenſe will
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170289:52"/> be, that <hi>The coming of Chriſt is the accidental cauſe of perſecution</hi> (namely through mens malice) or <hi>Men would take occaſion, from the coming of Chriſt to ſtir up per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions.</hi> Here <hi>the coming of Chriſt</hi> is the Antecedent. <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions ſhould ariſe upon occaſion thereof,</hi> the Conſequent. <hi>Becauſe I came, perſecutions will follow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. There is another Adjunct to the Connex, or as one ſhould ſay, joyned to it as it were in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity, not to be meaſured out of the preciſe proportion of the form alone; but with a reſpect had, as well to the nature of the matter, as to the nature of God who is the witneſſe. In ſuch connexes, (whether they have relation to God or man) though nothing <hi>in eſſe,</hi> or in being, is ſomewhat ſet down in <hi>poſſe,</hi> or poſſibility; and ſomewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170289:52"/> according to the matter on Gods part, as Deut. 32.41. if <hi>I whet, &amp;c.</hi> Here is the <hi>poſſe,</hi> or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, and when it pleaſeth him, it is to be underſtood, he will doe it. On our part, in exhortations, monitions, with promiſes and threatnings, &amp;c. is ſet down the <hi>poſſe,</hi> or poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the ſecond Covenant, not of the firſt oeconomically pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. See Dr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> in his Sermon <hi>Of Perſeverance.</hi> Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the matter alſo, either neceſſary, or indifferent: of the neceſſary, is laid down, <hi>it ought</hi> or <hi>ought not:</hi> of the indifferent, <hi>it may,</hi> or <hi>it may not;</hi> or <hi>it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient,</hi> or <hi>it is not expedient.</hi> Which may alſo be obſerved in other axiomes of the ſame matter, as Mat. 10.32,33. For ſeeing the force of Divine teſtimony (as theſe are in an eminent degree)
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170289:53"/> proceeds from Gods infinite Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, vertue, and benevolence: We muſt look we doe not attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to any Divine ſaying, any unworthy or leſſe then worthy thing.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. This connex, if it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain nothing which is abſolute in it, and the parts be ſingle; the axiome may be propoſed (being not very long) as one only Doctrine, and thoſe things which are involved in it, be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from it as Uſes, if any one ſhall think the ſentence to be elliptick, and that theſe things which are involved are to be ſupplyed: I will not much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend againſt it. Sometimes it will not be amiſſe to avoid the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience of too prolixe a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. See an example in the laſt Section. This axiome is laid without any note, Jam. 5.13.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170289:53"/> Where in the antecedent <hi>poſſe, may,</hi> is included in the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent alſo, <hi>debere, it ought.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. If there be a copulate compoſition in this axiome (as that Chap. 5. Sect. 2.) it will be ſo likewiſe in the treaty, Rom. 10.9. <hi>If thou ſhalt confeſſe with thy mouth, &amp;c.</hi> The axiomes (paſſing over what is abſolute in either part) <hi>are</hi> 1. <hi>To confeſſe with the mouth, &amp;c. is required to ſalvation.</hi> 2. <hi>To beleeve in the heart, &amp;c. is required to ſalvation.</hi> 3. <hi>If thou doe both this and that, thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">12. If a copulate compoſition be alſo in the conſequent, and that it be large, it may be ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily contracted into one no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, containing all its parts, that the Doctrines which are framed out of it applyed to the parts of the antecedent, may be
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170289:54"/> the brieflier propoſed. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the antecedent that it may be the eaſilier applyed to the parts of the conſequent. So in the Commination, where there is ſuch a copulation, the parts may be laid as tending to the evill denounced, Luke 12.45,46. Where out of the Hypotheſis of the Diſſemblable behaviours of the ſervant, there is foretold a Diſſemblable event, <hi>If that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ſay, &amp;c.</hi> (as he may, but ought not to ſay.) Axiome. 1. <hi>That ſervant ſaith in his heart, My Lord delayeth his comming, it tends to damnation.</hi> 2. <hi>He begins to beat the men ſervants, and the maid ſervants, it tends, &amp;c.</hi> 3. <hi>To eat, drink, and be drunken, tends, &amp;c.</hi> 4. <hi>If he doe both that, and that, and this, be ſhall be damned.</hi> Out of which laſt axiome may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a Climax, or gradation
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170289:54"/> of ſin, by way of uſe. And as we contracted the conſequent to one notion, that the Doctrines might be propoſed ſo much the brieflier out of it applyed to the parts of the conſequent, ſo may the antecedent alſo be contracted to one, that it may be eaſilier applyed to the parts of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent. Hence the fifth axiome. <hi>If this ſervant be ſo deſperately wicked, his Lord will come upon him, in a day when he looketh not for him, and in an hour when he is not aware.</hi> 6. <hi>If he be ſuch a one, he will out him in ſunder.</hi> 7. <hi>He will appoint him his portion with unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</hi> 8. The whole axiome out of the parts propoſed on both ſides. Out of this axiome may be obſerved, 1. A Climax or gradation in the conſequent, or the degrees of puniſhment threatned to that ſervant. 2. The
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170289:55"/> proportion between the ſin in the antecedent, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the conſequent. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>He ſaith, the Lord delayeth his coming: the Lord will come in a day when he looketh not for him, in an hour when he is not ware.</hi> Alſo he beats, &amp;c. The Lord will cut him in ſunder. Likewiſe, <hi>He gorges, and makes himſelf drunk with an immoderate portion of food, and wine. The Lord will appoint him his portion of food, and wine. The Lord will appoint him his portion with unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of a negate, or denyed Connex.</head>
                  <p n="13">13. The negate connex (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be denyed by prepoſing a negation to the whole axiome, or by more openly denying the conſequence) doth no more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite a doctrine in parts then an affirmate.</p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:170289:55"/>
                  <p n="14">14. Becauſe there would be no place for a negate connex in Scripture, unleſſe the Antecedent did not inferre the conſequent affirmate; but oftentimes it doth not inferre it, becauſe the parts are divers amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Thence it ſeemes to be, ſuch an affirmate is more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denyed, as for the affection of the parts, by the diſcrete or ſevered of <hi>quanquam,</hi> or <hi>tamen, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though,</hi> or nevertheleſſe (which alſo expreſſes the diverſity of parts) then by the negate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex, which only denies the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent to be inferred. But when it is denyed by an axiome of this or another kind (as ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually it may be) the axiome ſo denying, muſt be referred to it own proper claſſis.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. If the firſt which hath affinity with the Connex, be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170289:56"/> under a ſtricter note, or if it doth bear a ſtricter; though the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation doth break the bond, yet the antecedent under ſuch a note, remains as granted. The conſequent in the mean time (whether it be true in it ſelf, or falſe) by the negation of the ſequel is left in the middle as in a preciſe connex. A more ſtrict note is [<hi>Cum, though</hi>] or [<hi>quando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidem, for becauſe</hi>] Rom. 9.7. <hi>Not becauſe they are the ſeed of</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, <hi>are they all children,</hi> the cauſall conjunction ſhall here bear a ſtrict note; not though you be (or <hi>although you are</hi>) <hi>the Seed of</hi> Abraham, are ye his ſons, ſaith the Apoſtle to the Jews, who would inferre the Conſequent out of the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; as if he had ſaid, <hi>though ye be the Seed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>yet it doth not follow, that ye are all ſons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170289:56"/>
                  <p n="16">16. And if this axiome, which this in Scripture doth contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict be ſo abſurd, that it layes a falſehood in the antecedent; the antecedent which will not bear a ſtricter note, doth conſtitute a Doctrine, 2 Cor. 11. In the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent of the Diſcrete the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle diſpoſeth ſuch an axiome. <hi>Not</hi> (the queſtion being equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to the negation) <hi>that I doe not love you, have I been</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>not burthenſome to you.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſeemes to obviate a male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous mans ſaying. <hi>Becauſe</hi> Paul <hi>doth not love us, therefore will he take nothing of us,</hi> to whom the Apoſtle oppoſes this contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory <hi>Not, &amp;c.</hi> [<hi>Quia, becauſe</hi>] is a more larger conjunction in the negate, and may be taken either as granting, or indifferently, as of he ſaid; Whether I love you, or not love you; the not loving,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170289:57"/> doth not inferre the not being burthenſom. And truly the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of man is ſo much larger then the portion of words, that it can hardly be bound and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by words in a ſentence; but at ſome time it may eſcape into a various ſenſe, unleſſe the ſcope of the place and context, &amp;c. be conſidered. Yet the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent is aſſerted under a ſtricter note. But this was not the ſenſe of the Apoſtle, but by the interrogation and queſtion equivalent to the negation, and his appeal to God touching his affection, as it ſhould ſeeme; and by the ſubjunction of the true cauſe in the 12. verſe, he doth rather inſinuate the contrary to this antecedent, which he doth likewiſe abundantly profeſſe in another place.</p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:170289:57"/>
                  <p n="17">17. The negation here ſeemes ſometimes not only to take away the bond, and ſo the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, but the conſequent alſo, eſpecially the more vehement, Rom. 6.15. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>what then, &amp;c.</hi> where <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as verſ. 1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>what then ſhall we ſin,</hi> &amp; 2 Cor. 11.11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>wherefore, &amp;c.</hi> (though elſewhere it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as Rom. 9.30,32.) ſeems to be a preparation to conſute the Prolepſis, or inconſequent infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: as if he ſhould ſay, You are inclined of things rightly ſpoken, to inferre things which are not right. <hi>We muſt not ſin, not becauſe we are not under the law.</hi> Omitting the Antecedent (which here is ſet down in the Diſcrete) 1. axiome, <hi>That we muſt not ſin.</hi> 2. <hi>Not for this cauſe.</hi> 3. <hi>This ought to be abominated, and prayed againſt,</hi> ſo Rom. 6.1. (where
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170289:58"/> the antecedent ſeemes to lay down nothing. 1. <hi>We ought not to remain in ſin.</hi> 2. <hi>No (not to this end) that grace may abound.</hi> 3. <hi>It is abominable, and a thing to be prayed againſt,</hi> for a man to remain in ſin to that end.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. Becauſe the reaſon of the finall cauſe is the unitive force of the axiome out of the end, and the thing which lyeth under this reaſon, is not alwayes produced, but is judged to be under the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the agent who is to produce it: but that which is held to be the <hi>medium,</hi> or means, uſeth to be in the external or reall act: hence it ſeemes to be that the negation which takes away the reaſon of the end, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom leaves the Doctrine in the Antecedent, but rather ſometimes leaves the Conſequent, in which that is diſpoſed which is eſteemed
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170289:58"/> the means by thoſe whom this axiome contradicts. As; <hi>I came not to judge the world, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Connex.</head>
                  <p n="19">19. Sometimes the abſolute conſideration of the end, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of the means, ſometimes of both may be omitted, and the means be joyned to the end, to conſtitute the Doctrine. As in the example of the 6. Sect. The firſt axiome being premiſed, the ſecond will be, <hi>He came to ſeek us that were loſt.</hi> 3. <hi>He came to ſave us.</hi> 4. <hi>He came to ſeek and ſave us.</hi> So in the parallel place, Mat. 18.11. <hi>It was loſt.</hi> 2. <hi>The Son of man came to ſave that.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="20">20. Sometimes it may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as a ſingle axiome, and be ſo treated of, Joh. 12.47. <hi>I came to ſave the world,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>To
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170289:59"/> ſave the world is the end of my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> 1. <hi>I came.</hi> 2. <hi>To ſave the world is the lend of this my coming.</hi> Likewiſe the negate or deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>I came not to judge the world;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>I came not to this end.</hi> In the ſame manner from the event. <hi>To ſend the ſword will be the event of this my coming. To ſend peace will not be the event,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. 2 Chron. 7.13,14. This axiome ſayeth ſomewhat in the parts, as well in reſpect of God, as of man. The chief arguments are, The fault (pre ſuppoſed, ver. 13. expreſſed the 14.) which is illative of the puniſhment, the puniſhment of repentance, and repentance of acceptation. <hi>Si, if. If I puniſh, (or if when I puniſh) they repent, then will I accept.</hi> This axiome connexed, contains the connex in the antecedent, and the Copulate in the Conſequent.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170289:59"/> The Connex involved in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent, conſiſts of the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in three members, propoſed under a disjunctive note, but looſely &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>numeratively taken, and of the conſequent in four members, under the copulate: the conſequent of the connex com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the whole conſiſts of three members under the copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative alſo. The firſt Doctrine, (according to the rule, Sect. 8. &amp; 9.) <hi>God can, andwhen he thinks it fit, ſhuts up the heavens</hi> (the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration from the end or event) <hi>that there may be no rain.</hi> 2. <hi>Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he commands the Locuſts, &amp;c.</hi> 3. <hi>God can, and when he pleaſeth, ſendeth peſtilence amongſt his people.</hi> 4. <hi>That, or this, or the other, he can, and when he pleaſeth, he doth, to his ſinning people:</hi> either all theſe, or ſome ſuch like thing, as appears by the analogy of other places,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170289:60"/> for here is not intended a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat enumeration. But this may be obſerved in the Uſe. Then in the conſequent of the connex involved in the antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the whole (having ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviated the antecedent of this, and the conſequent of the whole, according to the rule, Sect. 12.) theſe Doctrines are contained, (having premiſed to theſe that abſolute one in this conſequent, namely, <hi>The name of the Lord is called upon his people</hi>) The firſt (according to the rule, Sect. 11.) <hi>It is required to acceptance, that Gods people upon whom, &amp;c. when he puniſheth, doe humble it ſelf.</hi> 2. <hi>That it pray.</hi> 3. <hi>That it ſeek his face.</hi> 4. <hi>That it turn from its wicked wayes.</hi> Then from either part of the whole antecedent abbreviated, and applyed to the conſequent, theſe Doctrines. 1. <hi>If
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170289:60"/> God puniſhing, his people doe all theſe things, he will hear from heaven.</hi> 2. <hi>Will forgive their ſin.</hi> 3. <hi>Will heal their land.</hi> Laſtly, the whole axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome. <hi>If when I have ſhut up the heaven that there be no rain, or have commanded the Locuſt, &amp;c. my people, &amp;c. then will I hear from heaven, &amp;c.</hi> Out of which axiome, the order of Divine Providence towards ſinners may be obſerved.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. Of the Diſcrete, or Severed.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p n="1">1. THe judgement of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete is, that the parts are true, and ſevered. It doth exhibit, the parts firſt to be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, (unleſſe ſome abſolute
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170289:61"/> be involved) then the diſcretion or ſeparation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Diſcrete ſeemes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be as it were compoſed of two Diſcretes, ſo that the conſequent of the firſt from [<hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though and notwithſtanding</hi>] involve in it the antecedent of the laſt, from [<hi>not, and but</hi>] and another Divers be ſet to it in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, Luke 4. ver. 27. (as alſo 25.) Where [although] is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>and</hi>] is read for [<hi>notwithſtanding, or yet</hi>] <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many Lepers were in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>in the time of</hi> Elizeus <hi>the Prophet, yet none of them were cleanſed, but</hi> Naaman <hi>the</hi> Syrian. Axiomes. 1. <hi>There were many, &amp;c.</hi> 2. <hi>None of them were cleanſed.</hi> 3. <hi>Though there were many, &amp;c. yet none, &amp;c.</hi> 4. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aman <hi>the</hi> Syrian <hi>was cleanſed.</hi> 5. <hi>None of them, but, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Diſſemblables which might
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170289:61"/> have agreed in quality, might be fully enunciated by ſuch a Diſcrete, that the Protaſis may be under [<hi>although</hi>] a negation of the fimilitude under [<hi>notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi>] the diverſe quality un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der [<hi>but</hi>].</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Such a Diſcrete is often met withall, but ſo that for brevity ſake, the conſequent of the firſt be omitted, and the Divers which ſhould be ſet to that Conſequent, in ſtead of it, may under [<hi>notwithſtanding</hi>] be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to the Antecedent, Prov. 20.17. As if it were more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed. <hi>Though the bread of deceit be ſweet to a man, yet</hi> [it doth not continue ſo, but] <hi>afterward his mouth ſhall be filled with gravel.</hi> That which is meant to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood therein, may well be brought for a fuller explication of the axiome, but be omitted in
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170289:62"/> the conſtitution of the doctrines: it abſence being abundantly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, being ſet in its Divers place, which ſounds ſomewhat that is greater: Axiomes. 1. <hi>The bread of deceit is ſweet,</hi> (namely to a man that is addicted to it). 2. <hi>His mouth ſhall be filled with gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 3. <hi>Afterward</hi> (that is to ſay, after this momentary ſweetneſſe) <hi>it ſhall be filled with gravel.</hi> 4. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be ſweet yet afterwards, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Theſe notes [<hi>although, and notwithſtanding</hi>] ſeeme to expreſſe the nature of Diſcretion, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifting in a leſſer diſcordance, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe notes doe hardly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a greater, but doe only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate that things ſo Diſcreted or ſevered might have convened and come together, and that ſometimes they are ſevered with a great offence, or vertue. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Scripture they are often
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170289:62"/> ſet down, as well for aggravation of ſin, (as 2 Chr. 36.15,16. Pſal. 55.12, &amp;c. Amos 4.6, &amp;c.) as for the praiſe of vertue, (as Job 2.3. Pſ. 44.17, &amp;c. 119.52 &amp; 83, &amp;c.)</p>
                  <p n="6">6. [<hi>Although</hi>] is often meant, and the [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] is ſet for [<hi>but</hi>] as Prov. 23.7. So [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] Matth. 11.25. &amp; [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] Rom. 6.17.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Becauſe the Diſcrete (as we have ſaid) oftentimes doth more clearly deny the affirmed Connex, then the negate connex it ſelf; and the negate connex ſometimes proceeds from feigned parts, ſo the negate connex of feigned parts is oftentimes propoſed under notes, and after the manner of a Diſcrete. Yea ſometimes, to deny the ſtronglier, it aſſumes unto it ſelf a greater feigned part, then the Author of the affirmate could probably conceive. Wherefore it obtains
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170289:63"/> its chief uſe under theſe notes, in Scriptures alſo, in amplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c. It may then be ſo propoſed by the Preacher, as it is found in Scripture, and more perſpicuouſly then if it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained in its own form. In the mean while we muſt know that it is not of the Diſcrete judgment (which requires the truth of the parts, but of the Connex; and that the Doctrine in parts is no better, then the formall negate connex it ſelf. But when it aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes a greater ſeigned part, then could be ſuppoſed by the Author of the affirmate, it may well be explicated, by adding the Reddition of a greater feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed part, which in ſuch ſentences is either to be underſtood, meant, or at leaſt doth neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. To this ſeemes might be referred that of Obad. v. 4. <hi>Edom</hi>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:170289:63"/> might reaſon with it ſelf. If I ſtrengthen my ſelf in high places, (for it was a mountainous coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey) I ſhall not be caſt down. To whom the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Though thou exalt thy ſelf as the Eagle, though thou ſet thy neſt among the ſtars, thence will I bring thee down</hi> [not only out of thine high places] The judgement is Not <hi>if thou didſt exalt thy ſelf,</hi> and not <hi>thou ſhould by me be caſt down.</hi> But the ſame ſenſe is more perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly enunciated under [<hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam,</hi> &amp; <hi>tamen, although</hi> and yet] ſo Ier. 37.10, &amp;c. If any one will contend that theſe are properly diſcrete ſayings: Let him imagin I ſet down this fection here for his ſake, becauſe I would breed no contention, yet I would not have him think it to be of the Diſcrete judgement.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:170289:64"/>
                  <head>Of the Diſcrete Negate or denied.</head>
                  <p n="8">8. We ſeldom meet with a Diſcrete negate directly, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally. If it be denyed by the Copulate or Connex (as it may be) theſe are to be referred to its proper Claſſis.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. Of the Disjunct or Disjoyned.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p n="1">1. THe judgement of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct truly and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken is, that one one only is true.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It exhibites no Doctrine (except the abſolute, if any doe happen) but onely it
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170289:64"/> ſelf true, in the true disjunction of the parts, Luke 16.13. <hi>a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of two maſters</hi> (who command contrary things) <hi>will either hate the one, and love the other: or will hold to the one, and deſpiſe the other.</hi> Here is a Disjunct with a copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in each part. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the one, and</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the other,</hi> ſeeme to have the force of a demonſtrative: as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Either he will hate this, and love the other, or will hold to this, and deſpiſe the other.</hi> Here are two abſolutes contained ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule, Ch. 4. Sect. 14.1. <hi>The ſcrvant will hold to that Maſter which he loves.</hi> 2. <hi>Him which he hates, he will deſpiſe.</hi> The co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation in the parts is ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the disjunctive note, by which the truth is indetermined either concerning this or that part. The axiome it ſelf offers it ſelf to be treated out of theſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170289:65"/> parts. Then the relative confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, <hi>Becauſe either the one,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>therefore no ſervant can ſerve two masters.</hi> 3. Though com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Disjunct axiomes are not frequent in Scripture, yet the disjunctive notes are often found in other axiomes, but for the moſt part looſely taken for the enumeration of parts, ſo far as they conſent with the whole, not for the disjoyning of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween themſelves, whereby the truth of the only one may be expreſſed. In which ſenſe they ſeeme to be taken rather copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, then disjunctively. Yet this enumeration is ſomet mes founded on perfect disjunction, ſo far as theſe parts are disjoyned in reſpect of the ſingulars un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the whole. Phil. 1.20. <hi>Chriſt ſhall be magnified in my body, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be by life, or by death.</hi> The
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170289:65"/> diſjunction is compleat, [<hi>Every magnification of Chriſt in the Apoſtles body, is either by life, or by death</hi>] by which the parts are voided, and it is ſignified that no ſingular magnification can be in the body both by life, and by death, but by one. But the Apoſtle intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another ſenſe, doth very fitly apply both parts to the whole. <hi>Both by life he ſhall be magnified, and by death he ſhall be magnified.</hi> And therefore the judgement is copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. See the like example, Ch. 8. Sect. 1. Sometimes this enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is grounded on incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Disjunction, as Chap. 8. Sect. <hi>ult.</hi> The thing both wayes comes to one: and by the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the diſpoſition, the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of others alſo, will be eaſie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170289:66"/>
                  <head>Of the Negate or denyed Disjunct.</head>
                  <p n="4">4. If we meet with a direct negate, it yeelds no more axiomes then the affirmate. Indirectly it may be denyed by the Copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late affirmed out of negative parts, which doth not admit of one true, out of the affirmate, which doth not admit of an on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. Of the Syllogiſm.</head>
               <p>IF the Text be of a Syllogiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal judgement, we muſt frame an Analy ſis before it, ſhewing the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170289:66"/> concluſion, then the premiſes, then the <hi>Crypſis,</hi> if any there be, So that the Syllogiſm may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in its proper form. Firſt the ſeveral axiomes muſt be handled. Laſtly, there muſt be an axiome made out of the premiſes, with a concluſion by the illative note, to ſhew the inference of the concluſion out of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. It matters not ſo much to the order, whether the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion or the premiſes be firſt handled, but that the ſeries of the words in the Text may end the controverſie. Seeing that in their abſolute conſideration they ſeeme to ſtand collaterally; and though between them there be alway a neceſſity, of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, yet there is none ſuch of the conſequent. But if the Antecedent doe contain <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the wherefore,</hi> of the concluſion
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170289:67"/> that is rightlyeſt treated of in the firſt place; to the end, that when you ſhall be come to treat of the concluſion, we may have <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the wherefore,</hi> at hand, as a thing known before. Though in ſuch things the wherefore may be omitted in the treaty of the concluſion, becauſe it offers it ſelf ſoon enough in the laſt axiome, unleſſe according to the <hi>Crypſis,</hi> Chap. 4. Sect. 24. it be otherwiſe diſpoſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If there ſhall ſeeme to be no intent of taking away the doubt, and the analyſis ſhall proceed well, according to the axiomatical judgement (though not without rational conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) and that the full ſenſe of the place may be had by it; it will not be neceſſary to reſolve the Text into a Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtical conſideration, every time
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170289:67"/> as we ſhall have power ſo to doe. Seeing that, for as much as belongeth to the thing, it is ſufficiently contained in that which is firſt a kin to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex, and may be treated out of its rule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. Of the Explication of the Axiome, or of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</head>
               <p>HItherto of the preparation to the Doctrine. The treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it followeth.</p>
               <p>Firſt the terms of the axiome, are to be explicated according as they are taken in Scripture, atd referring them to their place
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170289:68"/> in the body of Divinity. That term is alwayes to be explicated firſt, which makes good the way to the underſtanding of the reſt, and doth not require the explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the reſt before hand.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the fuller explication, if need be, ſuch queſtions may be propouuded and reſolved, as ſhall ſeeme to conduce to the better opening of the ſenſe of the axiome: as alſo ſuch illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be added, as may, more throughly imprint them in the minds of the hearers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In a ſingle axiome, the conſequent part, as for the moſt part larger, may be firſt explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Compoſite one, let the explication of the antecedent precede, and that of the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent follow.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He that will explain well, ought to be well exerciſed in
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170289:68"/> Scriptures, and in the Idiome of thoſe languages wherein they are written, not without reſpect to the Oriental notions in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, and the conferring of the ſame with the Greek, not without reſpect to the Hebrew in the Greek, as alſo to the Greek done by the Septuagint, and to the <hi>Targum Judaicum,</hi> for the underſtanding of both. He muſt not be carryed away by any prejudice, he ought to love the truth ſincerely, and wholly ſubject himſelf unto it. For the interpretation of words or phraſes, either ſingle or in Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxis, he may make uſe of Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeologies and Concordances. For the finding out of the ſenſe, he muſt look as well to the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of faith expreſſed in mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt places, as to the ſcope of the place conferring it with
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170289:69"/> other ſemblable or diſſemblable places, conſidering the context, and in it the occaſion, end, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of perſons, place, time, and finally the coherency with the Antecedents and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. Of the Confirmation of the Axiome ſhewing both the
<list>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the what &amp;</item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the wherefore.</item>
                  </list>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THe Axiome may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by parallel places of Scripture, and thoſe, if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, moſt evident (except thoſe which are no more Divine teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170289:69"/> howſoever they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in holy Scripture, but as the Scripture ſaith ſuch a one or ſuch a one ſpake thus) Then by other arguments, <hi>a poſteriori, from that which followeth,</hi> that we ſhall find in Scriptures.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though no weights of reaſon can adde any thing to the firmneſſe of that which is grounded upon divine teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, nevertheleſſe Scripture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though above, yet not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt good reaſon, and doth not take away, but perfect it, it will not be much from the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſometimes to make uſe of reaſons, and other things, as drawn from the art of Nature, if they ſhall be judged fitting, eaſie and profitable for the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, whereby they may the better reliſh and retain Divine truth in <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the what</hi> of it.</p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:170289:70"/>
               <p n="3">3. And though alſo the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Fathers, and of the whole Church, yea of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures being put all together can adde nothing to Divine antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, on which the axiomes of holy Scripture are grounded: yet it will not be abſurd ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to ſhew that this axiome was received, and approved of in this ſenſe by the Ancient Church, and its Heroes: yea the teſtimony of thoſe who are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Church, and of the enemies to it, may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and in ſome caſes is more available then that of its own children.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Yet theſe confirmations drawn from humane reaſon and teſtimony, ought to be brought more ſparingly, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out choice, having alſo regard unto the genius of the hearers;
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170289:70"/> adding moreover, if need be, ſome difference to make a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction between theſe, and them that are from Divine teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Though to argue the whole, the induction of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verals would be of great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: yet becauſe it would be too prolixe to enumerate the ſingulars, they might be brought under ſome certain heads, by one or more perfect diſtributions, and ſo the whole be evinced. If ſome inſtances of many bee brought, as they doe of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves illuſtrate and exemplifie the whole; ſo if they doe poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially contain the reſt, or if there be no other thing in the reſt to be ſeen, they may very well be thought to have the power of confirmation alſo.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:170289:71"/>
               <p n="6">6. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or the wherefore is to be fetched out of the proper cauſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The proper demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wherefore, though it be but only one, of one axiome, yet it may conſiſt of many members, as of partial cauſes, which therefore are to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, and in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity or wholeneſſe applyed to the confirmation of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The fact is chiefly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated of the efficient out of its
<list>
                     <item>faculty.</item>
                     <item>end.</item>
                  </list> The fact of the agent by reaſon, is demonſtrated of him by his directing knowledge (power in lawfull things) his decreeing will, in which may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170289:71"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>ſignifications, by word, oath, pledge, and the like.</item>
                     <item>motives
<list>
                           <item>from without.</item>
                           <item>from within,</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list> which have a reſpect to the end, and potentially. The Power ſometimes taken at large, may alſo comprehend knowledge in it.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The occupated adjunct, may be demonſtrated of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, by the formal reaſon of it, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="cryptic">
                  <head>Crypſis.</head>
                  <p n="10">10. If the confirmation of the the axiome cannot be had in <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the what, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in ſuch, through the deficiency of matter, the rule fails.</p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:170289:72"/>
                  <p n="11">11. The Hiſtorical axiome of the fact, where <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the what is deficient or wanting, may not unfitly be illuſtrated from the like example, ſhewing how he by whom the ſaying is made, or others in ſuch a buſineſſe have done the like. Which though it does not prove this hath been done, yet it makes it probable. Alſo cauſes as probable may be brought, which things ſtanding thus, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons being thus affected, uſe to produce ſuch effects.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:170289:72"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. Of the Vindication of the Axiome from Objections.</head>
               <p>SO hath the treaty of the Doctrine been directed in the
<list>
                     <item>Explication.</item>
                     <item>Confirmation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Though Objections may ſometimes be brought uſefully againſt any part of the Method, yet it will not be out of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to aſſign a fixed, and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite place to thoſe things which are brought or alleadged, againſt the Doctrine or fundamental axiome.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Objections may ariſe either out of ſome other Text of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, in ſhew contradicting
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170289:73"/> ours, or out of ſome reaſoning grounded upon the principles commonly received. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer are anſwered by reconciling the places of Scripture one with the other; the latter by diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the weakneſſe thereof out of Scripture and true reaſon.</p>
               <div type="cryptic">
                  <head>Crypſis.</head>
                  <p n="3">3. It will not be adviſedly done, to buzze many, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubtile objections into the hearers Ears, which peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would not otherwiſe enter into their thought, and which it is not ſo eaſie to root out, and dangerous to leave, in their mindes, ſo that oftentimes it will not be amiſſe to leave out all this place, and proceed directly from the confirmation of the Doctrine to the Uſe.</p>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:170289:73"/>
                  <p n="4">4. If the hearers be poſſeſſed with a prejudicate opinion againſt the truth of the axiome, it will be good firſt to anſwer their objections, before we come to the confirmation of the axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome, that having removed the prejudice, our Confirmation may gain more belief and and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Objections of the firſt kind, may, not unfitting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, be ſometimes propounded by way of queſtion, and reſolved in the explication of the axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:170289:74"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV. Of Uſes in General.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>HItherto the firſt part of the Method, of Doctrine. The other of Uſes followeth.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Seeing the Word of God, is (not the height, much leſſe the miſtake of humane underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) the power of God to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: there ought great care to be taken in the applying of the ſame to the mind of man: that this arm of God may be laid bare, and in the evidence of his Spirit, and the radiation or bright ſhining of the Principle, or of the Doctrine, in the uſe, or in the conſectary it may be accommodated to the hearers, ſo that the uſe may be as a cart,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170289:74"/> by which a divine axiome is brought to the mind, and as it were a ſpecification of it upon the ſame, as in ſeveral reſpects it ſhall agree thereunto.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As the Arguments or places of invention, repreſenting unto us the various affections of things amongſt themſelves doe yeeld foundations of deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo the force of affections the firmneſſe and neceſſity of the ſame. That we may the better judge of theſe things, it will be worth the while ſometimes to make out of the Doctrine the Antecedent, and out of the uſe the Conſequent of the affirmed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex, and ſo contemplate them in the judgement of that axiome, that we may ſee how the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent infers the Conſequent. But becauſe the ſeveral diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and placing of the ſame
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170289:75"/> thing, doth oftentimes give much light for the clear appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending of it: we may contradict that connex (either by a Negate of its own kind, or by a Diſcrete affirmate out of the contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſequent) that the falſhood of the oppoſite may appear. We may, if the matter will give us leave, convert it into a a ſingle axiome, and make it the Major of the Syllogiſm, the Antecedent or the Doctrine the Minor, the Conſectary or the uſe, the Concluſion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The ſame uſe of the Axiom, if it be to be had any where expreſly in the Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, doth commend a preſent application. Here if the thing propoſed to the Hearers in the Conſectary, be not contained in the Text, nor the nature of it ſufficiently known; it will
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170289:75"/> be needfull, as well to inform the hearers, as alſo that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction may more clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, preſently upon the entry of the ſame Uſe, to explicate what is meant by it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It will not be alwayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to deduce all thoſe Uſes which by a Logical conſequence may be deduced from the axiom; nor follow prolixely thoſe which we deduce, nor refer thoſe to ſeveral heads which may be referred (unleſſe peradventure it may ſeeme needful to diluci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date ſome, under the uſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, that thoſe which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the heart, and affections may in them be more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally urged) but when we have deduced as many as we can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently, it ſhall be lawful to refer them to thoſe heads, be they more or leſſe, in which
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170289:76"/> they may be handled moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. If the ſame Uſes may be deducted from ſeveral axiomes in the Text, they may be ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed, that no axiome may either abound in Uſes, or be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of them.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. In the Uſes of the ſame Claſſis may ſome order be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, according to the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude or relation as they have, as well among themſelves as to thoſe arguments in the axiome, of which they principally ariſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="cryptic">
                  <head>Crypſis.</head>
                  <p n="7">7. It is not to be expected that all ſingle axiomes ſhould afford thoſe kinds of uſes which are expreſſed in the Method, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in ſome peradventure we may find them all.) Let us
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170289:76"/> therefore be contented with thoſe which ſpontaneally doe follow out of the axiome: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let us trouble our ſelves, or wreſt the Text to extract ſuch things, as cannot be had.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. When the ſame uſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth out of two or more axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes, it may moſt fittingly be put off to the laſt, but urged in virtue of all. And if thoſe axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes be to be handled in divers Sermons, ſo that ſome ſpace of time may intercede, this uſe may be briefly hinted at in the firſt, reſerving the fuller treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof to the laſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes from the Hypotheſis to the Theſis, or from the Species to the Genus.</head>
                  <p n="9">9. In the hypotheſis, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per axiome, we may conſider;
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170289:77"/> Firſt, the matter whether that be a fact, (under which we alſo comprehend the omiſſion) enun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated of its author, Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally good or evill, or any other arguments in which is attributed the
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>conſentaneum,</hi> or what is agreeable,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>diſſentaneum,</hi> what is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, or diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</item>
                     </list> Secondly, the propriety or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity, whether it be in the only or chief antecedent, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the conſequent alſo; or in ſome reſtrictive condition of time and place, &amp;c. expreſſed or of neceſſity to be underſtood. <hi>All the Saints ſalute you,</hi> that is to ſay, which were then at <hi>Rome,</hi> Phil. 4.22.</p>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:170289:77"/>
                  <p n="10">10. The Argumentation from thence is either
<list>
                        <item>Immediate,</item>
                        <item>Mediate, where the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium or means is in
<list>
                              <item>all
<list>
                                    <item>to <hi>poſſe,</hi> or may be, in affirmates,</item>
                                    <item>to <hi>poſſe non,</hi> or may not be, in negates.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>actions or omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<list>
                                    <item>all
<list>
                                          <item>to propend or incline to,</item>
                                          <item>to propend or incline to not.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>if they be
<list>
                                          <item>neceſſary
<list>
                                                <item>to ought,</item>
                                                <item>to ought not.</item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                          <item>indifferent
<list>
                                                <item>then
<list>
                                                      <item>to be lawful.</item>
                                                      <item>to not be lawful.</item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>then
<list>
                                                      <item>to be expedient,</item>
                                                      <item>to not be expedient.</item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:170289:78"/>
                  <p n="11">11. But the <hi>medium</hi> or means follows the ſubject in relation of it to the attribute, in all in
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>poſſe,</hi> to may be.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>poſſe non,</hi> to not may be:</item>
                     </list> In all actions and omiſſions in
<list>
                        <item>propending or inclining to,</item>
                        <item>propending or inclining to not.</item>
                     </list> The <hi>medium</hi> or means followeth the kind of the action in the reſt. In which the nature of the action ought to be ſhewn whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of its kind it be neceſſary or indifferent.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. We may argue from ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſpecials in the Hypotheſis to ſeveral generals in the <hi>Theſis.</hi> We may alſo argue from the Hypotheſis to a manifold The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, according to the various re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects in the Hypotheſis. See an example, Sect. 17.</p>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:170289:78"/>
                  <p n="13">13. We may argue from the Hypotheſis to the Theſis in the like quality, as from the affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to the affirmate; from the negate to the negate: or in a diſſemblable quality, as from the affirmate to the negate, 1 Cor. 10. from the negate to the affirmate.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. The argumentation from the ſpecies to the genus holds only, according to that of the genus which is in the ſpecies, and ſo from all of that genus, to us, as of the ſame genus. Or if we take it <hi>a part,</hi> from the equall, the reaſon of the conſequence is from that community, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedes to us with that ſpecies; which community is the cauſe of that parity or equality, becauſe eſſences of things are in the indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, and the <hi>genus</hi> where it communicates, communicates the whole. And ſo fals to the ſame place.</p>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:170289:79"/>
                  <p n="15">15. A mediate argumentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on requires, firſt that the <hi>medium</hi> or means doe truly appertain to the Hypotheſis. Secondly, that from the Hypotheſis, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that means, we argue to the Theſis, ſo far as the means be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to that genus which is in the Hypotheſis.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. We may argue from the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis to the Theſis, by a redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicative term added to the genus applyed to the Hypotheſis, either mediately, or immediately; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is <hi>an effectual illation or inference, from the</hi> quatenus ipſum, as it is it ſelf, <hi>to the</hi> de omni, <hi>of all.</hi> Abraham <hi>as he was to be juſtified ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the reaſon of the ſecond Covenant,</hi> was juſtified by faith. <hi>Ergo</hi> every one that is ſo to be juſtified, is juſtified by faith.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. We may alſo argue from the Hypotheſis to the Theſis, in
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170289:79"/> that reſpect in which it will not bear the reduplicative term, ſo that under that reſpect it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that which ſhall bear that term. <hi>David,</hi> not as he was a believer, but being a believer, did commit adultery: <hi>Ergo,</hi> he could (but not as he was a believer, or according to that principle; but according to nature, which he had, common with all believers, hindred by no neceſſity from commiting ſuch a ſin) <hi>Ergo,</hi> a believer may commit adultery, or a devouring ſin. <hi>Ergo</hi> a King, <hi>Ergo</hi> a Prophet, <hi>Ergo</hi> one that had more then ſufficient help to the contrary, <hi>Ergo</hi> one who was abounding in, or cumulated with Gods bleſſings, may, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. And theſe few things I thought good to point at, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this head of Deduction from the Hypotheſis to the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170289:80"/> of which there is a frequent abuſe: not that I thought a thing of much latitude could be concluded in this ſhort compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, but that I might give others occaſion of ſearching out this place more diligently.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. Of the uſe of Inſtruction.</head>
               <p>IT remains that we treat of the uſe in ſpecie which hath reſpect to the
<list>
                     <item>mind or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</item>
                     <item>heart, or the will and affections.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt head of uſe is, in the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170289:80"/> applying of the Doctrine to the mind or underſtanding. And here, becauſe the heart or will hath a great influx into the mind (according to that, <hi>Thoſe things which we will, we eaſily believe</hi>) therefore it is lawful (though it is poſſible and cuſtomary to fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter exceedingly in this thing) it is lawfull (I ſay) in a good cauſe, to inſinuate ſomething ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hiddenly or openly, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may poſſeſſe the hearers affections, and by them, as by ſetting ſcaling ladders invade the fort of the mind.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The firſt Uſe, belonging to the mind, is Inſtruction, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming it with ſome Divine truth derived out of the axiome, and contained in it as in a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple. This uſe the Apoſtle ſeems to ſignifie by his (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>for inſtruction</hi>) 2 Tim. 3.16. To
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170289:81"/> this belong all the conſectarie ſpeculatives flowing from the Doctrine. This place may be amplyfied more, or leſſe, ſo it be done perſpicuouſly and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the capacity of the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
               <div type="cryptic">
                  <head>Crypſis.</head>
                  <p n="3">3. If the uſe of Inſtruction (as it ſometimes happens) may be referred alſo to ſome of thoſe, which have a reſpect to the heart, it will be more commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to leave this place void, then thoſe, eſpecially where the thing or matter of the heart is rather in agitation then that of the mind, and it is of more concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to have the affections mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or ſetled, then to have the underſtanding informed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:170289:81"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII. Of Refutation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THis uſe alſo hath a relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the mind. Its work is to obviate or meet with errors oppoſite to the Divine axiome. Either (in manner of an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote) to thoſe things, by which the hearers may any way be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered. Or (in manner of a remedy) againſt thoſe which begin to creep or take head amongſt them. To this ſeemes to have relation that of the Apoſtle <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>for reproof</hi>].</p>
               <p n="2">2. But when one makes uſe of this, he muſt again and again beware, leſt he refute and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thoſe for errors, which are not errors. For if it be woe
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170289:82"/> unto him (whoſoever he be) that cals light darkneſſe; much more woe ſhall it be to that Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, who in the place or ſtead, and name of God, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Chriſt, under the pretence of the holy Spirit, before the holy Angels and the Church, peradventure to the prejudice of Divine truth, revealed by the Son out of the boſome of the Father, for the exceeding good of man, ſhall not fear to doe this in contempt of the faithful and moſt dear ſervants of God, on whom he hath conferred ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding many gifts, for the good of others, and on which many ſouls depend.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Moreover, if he attribute to any one, an erroneous or hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal opinion, &amp; makes him guilty in that kind: he muſt be certain that he whom he ſo accuſeth,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170289:82"/> doth indeed maintain that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and alſo in that ſenſe, and degree both real, and mental, as is imputed to him. But of this he cannot be certain by any bodies teſtimony who is of the adverſe part, although he other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be no way an evill man. Who although he pretend to cite out of the Author him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the preciſe words in which the error or hereſie is thought to be contained; yet he ought not raſhly to be believed. For peradventure (which is the nature of prejudice, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially joyned with intempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) he takes one thing for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one Author for another, one word for another, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture he utters mutilated and half ſentences, or if whole, ill pointed; peradventure he addes ſomewhat of his own; perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170289:83"/> keeping the words, he ſeigneth to them another, and alien ſenſe wide from the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors mind: the text it ſelf and ſcope contradicting it. For all theſe things may be done not only fraudulently, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo through unskilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or perturbation of mind.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If he confute any under the name of ſome Church, or Congregation, he muſt look he doe not call in queſtion ſome private mens aſſertions, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived articles of that Church or Congregation. For it will be unjuſt to burden the whole with the errors of ſome, or to require that which ſome one holds, to be maintained by all.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If he undertake to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute ſome who hold opinions againſt our Church: he muſt firſt make that plain, that the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170289:83"/> which their opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts, is indeed an article of our Church, and not only his, or ſome other private ſpirits, though they be many.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If he doe not only accuſe the opinion which he confutes, and the defenders of it for the bare crime of error or falſehood, but alſo purſue them for blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, profane people, ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Evangelical conſort, joyned in affinity with hereticks and hereſies, which have been heretofore condemned, &amp;c. he muſt be ſo much the more wary, and certain of that which he ſpeaks. For the grievouſer the crime is, which is objected, the grievouſer is the injury, if it be objected falſely.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Finally, what error ſoever he brings upon the ſtage, let him doe it nervouſly, ſolidly, and
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170289:84"/> manifeſtly; leſt the reſutation vaniſh away, and the error ſtick faſt: but with an affection and ſpeech befitting the cauſe, and Chriſtian charity: leſt whileſt he takes care to free the hearers mindes from error, he fill them with malice and bitterneſſe; and by his example doe teach how to cauſe Religion to be from one end to the other evill ſpoken of, and hated by the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: then which things (if we will believe Scripture, rather then our own malignant nature) there can nothing be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to pure Religion.</p>
               <div type="cryptic">
                  <head>Crypſis.</head>
                  <p n="8">8. The uſe of Refutation may for the moſt part be omitted, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the error be ſuch as have found belief with our Auditors,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170289:84"/> or of which we are afraid in their behalf, or from which we may hope by their means to have others freed.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. In ſome neceſſary Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, we may proſecute the error, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite truth <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. Of Reprehenſion.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p n="1">1. NOw follow the uſes, which have reſpect to the heart, or will, and affections. But theſe eſpecially doe vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to themſelves all manner of Rh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>torical preparation; but not to be undertaken without the ſalt of wiſdom and gravity, as
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170289:85"/> is befitting a ſacred perſon and buſineſſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And here ſometimes may be ſomewhat mixed with the uſe which belongs to another, but obliquely, as they ſhall ſeem to conduce for the ſharpning or ſoftning of one another.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The uſes which belong to the heart, have a reſpect unto it, either as under ſome preſent diſtemperature, or diſpoſition, in regard of which it hath need of ſome correction or rectifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or in relation to ſome future thing.</p>
                  <p>Of the firſt kind are
<list>
                        <item>Reprehenſion,</item>
                        <item>Conſolation.</item>
                     </list> Theſe two ſeem to be contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Apoſtles [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>for correction.</hi>]</p>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:170289:85"/>
                  <p n="4">4. If the Doctrine doe afford a conſectary, which doth argue the evill of the ſin to lye upon our hearers, it may be applyed to them in the uſe of Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The formall object there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of this is ſin, of which the Author doth not yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent: The end to excite ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row or repentance: The <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> or means by which he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to this end, is by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and urging that evill both as preſent and as great.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The preſence of the evil may be demonſtrated from the notes or markes. And theſe may be taken chiefly from the proper adjuncts, and oppoſites with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>medium;</hi> becauſe that from theſe we may always argue, both affirmatively and negatively. The cauſes alſo may ſometimes
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170289:86"/> be taken for notes, unleſſe it be when we had rather make uſe of them, in the Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Dehortation. But in this thing the proper effects are exceeding uſefull. For though we cannot argue from them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatively and negatively, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the cauſe is not alwayes in the ſecond act, yet the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative argumentation is very evident and convictive: neither is the negative quite null, when the cauſe, if it were preſent, had all things preſent for to act. We may alſo make uſe of other notes as well affirmatives as nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. But the man of God, who will with dexterity aſſigne the notes (eſpecially in ſome caſes) muſt have ſenſes well exerciſed in Scriptures, and be well skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led both in the art of reaſoning,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170289:86"/> the nature of the humane ſoul, and the divers means of Gods operating: alſo the ſtate of man as well carnal as ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and the divers degrees of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in what ſtate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree he was in Scriptures from whoſe example he will argue, &amp;c. But away with all vain dreams of humane brain, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate experiments, confuſed and incertain collections, &amp;c. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with one making himſelf as a rule to all men, like a Pretor, and as it were ſitting on a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, gives ſentence on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſtate, having neither regard nor reſpect to the nature of things, or Gods own Word: though every one of us ſtands or fals to God alone, and his Word be the judge of all men, and the rule of all ſtates and degrees in order to God, and a
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170289:87"/> certain and infallible index of all manner of obliquity.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Thoſe things we have ſaid here of notes, may be uſefull in Conſolation, and chiefly in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. As the preſence of the evill is demonſtrated by the notes of the offence, ſo the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by the aggravations. The chief heads of aggravations may be taken out by the Scheme ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the end of the Chapter; which alſo hath place in the reſidue of uſes.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. To this act of Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion may alſo be added the act of Commination or Denuntia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of puniſhment, out of one or more manifeſt places of Scripture, with which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt thunders againſt that ſin.</p>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:170289:87"/>
                  <p n="11">11. But let this uſe more then any of the reſt, bring with it the force, and evidence of the Text or Doctrine from whence it is deduced. Here we muſt alſo make uſe (if there be any neceſſity to uſe them) of the moſt evident notes we can get; Like unto the bleating of the ſheep, &amp;c. 1 Sam. 15. to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover <hi>Saul's</hi> diſobedience.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. When ſubordinate ſins, and ſuch as are diſtinguiſhed by divers degrees, are to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, it will be moſt commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to begin with the leaſt, and ſo aſcend <hi>gradatim</hi> or by degrees. And ſo likewiſe in the aggravation of the ſame ſin. But here the privative op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is leſſer then the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. If it be requiſite to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſomewhat longer in repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170289:88"/> of ſome ſin: after the notes are given (if there be need of them) we may firſt argue from the diſhoneſty and unprofitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (where alſo the Commina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) in its latitude. Then with aggravations, ſhewing the more then vulgar magnitude of both, or of the firſt in ſome caſes, following alſo each degree of the ſaid ſin (if ſo you think fitting) from the leaſt to the higheſt, and that by divers heads and degrees of aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. To this head may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the <hi>Lamentation</hi> ſometimes uſed in Scripture, by which the Preacher ſometimes virtually and obliquely reprehends ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. This Lamentation is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<list>
                        <item>actually aſſumed,</item>
                        <item>foretold that it muſt be aſſumed.</item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:170289:88"/> And it is for
<list>
                        <item>ſin committed,</item>
                        <item>puniſhment
<list>
                              <item>preſent,</item>
                              <item>future.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list> That for ſin draws nearer to the nature of formal Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as having the object cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ſame formal reaſon. This for puniſhment is more oblique, as not having the ſame reaſon in the object, but that doth argue it, as the effect doth the proper cauſe. That princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally flows from the Preachers love to God, towards whom the ſin is. This from the love towards the neighbour, againſt whom the puniſhment is.</p>
                  <p>An example of Lamentation actually aſſumed for ſin, is to be had Iſai. 1.21.</p>
                  <p>For puniſhment
<list>
                        <item>preſent, Lam. 1. v. 1. to the 12.</item>
                        <item>future, Iſ. 22.4.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:170289:89"/>
                  <p>An example of a Lamentation which is foretold muſt be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, for ſin, 2 Cor. 12.21. For puniſhment, Iſa. 15.5.</p>
                  <p>And it may be uſed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<list>
                        <item>to this or that part ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</item>
                        <item>to both joyntly, ſo Luk. 13. v. 34, 35. And not without tears, c. 19.49.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>It may alſo be amply fied; Firſt by bewayling things or perſons, in which they who are bewayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed doe ſin, or are puniſhed, Jer. 9.10.</p>
                  <p>Secondly by
<list>
                        <item>Apoſtrophe,</item>
                        <item>Proſopopoeia.</item>
                     </list> By Apoſtrophe to the things or perſons, Iſa. 23.14. or to others,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170289:89"/> to whom it belongs to grieve for the ſin or puniſhment of thoſe who are reprehended. By Profopopoeia bringing in either the ſinners themſelves, Prov. 5.12. or the things, or perſons, in which they ſin or are puniſhed. Secondly, others alſo, and thoſe either condoling, Rev. 18.9. or deriding, Lam. 2.15.</p>
                  <p>The Lamentation which is foretold muſt be aſſumed; as for that part which hath a relation to the puniſhment, it may be added to amplifie the Denuntia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="cryptic">
                  <head>Crypſis.</head>
                  <p n="15">15. The notes may here be omitted, unleſſe it be when ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſins are of a more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile nature, then that they can be eaſily diſcerned; or the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170289:90"/> ſo obſtinate and pleaſing to themſelves, that they will not acknowledge themſelves to be vicious.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. To more prudent ſinners it will be ſufficient ſometimes briefly to have glanced at ſome ſin, and in a word have ſhewn how it is adverſe to the Text, or to the Doctrine. So we may altogether ſpare aggravations, unleſſe we will make uſe of ſome few, which ſhall ſeem moſt fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. The Commination, or Denuntiation may well be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, unleſſe it be when the ſin of its own nature is more grievous, or hath taken deep root, or the hearers are inclined and apt to fall into it.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. This uſe may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what mollified and ſweetened and be made no leſſe (and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170289:90"/> more) effectual if the Preacher doe ſacredly profeſſe, that he doth not of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and willingly deſcend to thoſe extreme remedies, but is drawn to it unwillingly, and with much grief. Eſpecially, if he ſhew himſelf ſuch, in the reſt of his life and ſpeech, with all manſuetude and lenity, that the hearers may believe he ſpeaks it truly. He may alſo by relating thoſe things which he judgeth to be excellent and praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in the hearers, both remove from himſelf the ſuſpicion of bitterneſſe and tartneſſe, and alſo admoniſh and exhort them not to ſtain the glory their virtues have acquired them, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of ſuch a foul ſin, or loſe their expected Crown.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:170289:91"/>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:170289:91"/>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:170289:92"/>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:170289:92"/>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:170289:93"/>
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:170289:93"/>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:170289:94"/>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:170289:94"/>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:170289:95"/>
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:170289:95"/>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:170289:96"/>
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:170289:96"/>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:170289:97"/>
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:170289:97"/>
                  <head>The chief heads of the aggravations of ſin.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. From cauſes
<list>
                           <item>Internal, through the nature or kind of ſin,</item>
                           <item>External
<list>
                                 <item>the efficient. <hi>A.</hi>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>A.</hi> From the efficient ſeen in the
<list>
                                          <item>Order of opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<list>
                                                <item>procreating</item>
                                                <item>preſerve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by
<list>
                                                      <item>inſiſting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</item>
                                                      <item>over-adding to</item>
                                                   </list> the tracks of others eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<list>
                                                      <item>notorious wicked ones.</item>
                                                      <item>heavily puniſhed ones.</item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                          <item>Manner of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perating
<list>
                                                <item>either
<list>
                                                      <item>ſolitary,</item>
                                                      <item>with others. <hi>B.</hi>
                                                         <p>
                                                            <hi>B.</hi> With others
<list>
                                                               <item>where from thoſe which ſin in that kind
<list>
                                                                     <item>the multitude,</item>
                                                                     <item>the conſpiracy.</item>
                                                                  </list>
                                                               </item>
                                                               <item>and thoſe
<list>
                                                                     <item>conſociates or fellows,</item>
                                                                     <item>unequals
<list>
                                                                           <item>principall, and eſpecially the evill,</item>
                                                                           <item>aſſiſtants, which the ſinner abuſes.</item>
                                                                        </list>
                                                                     </item>
                                                                  </list>
                                                               </item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </p>
                                                      </item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>or by it ſelf. <hi>C.</hi>
                                                   <p>
                                                      <hi>C.</hi> By it ſelf, as very wilfull. Here is to be conſidered
<list>
                                                         <item>The mind as it
<list>
                                                               <item>preſents
<list>
                                                                     <item>greater diſſwaſives,</item>
                                                                     <item>leſſer motives.</item>
                                                                  </list>
                                                               </item>
                                                               <item>is captivated
<list>
                                                                     <item>makes one wiſe to ſin,</item>
                                                                     <item>extends the deſire of ſinning.</item>
                                                                  </list>
                                                               </item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                         <item>The conſcience
<list>
                                                               <item>as it reclaims. <hi>D.</hi>
                                                                  <p>
                                                                     <hi>D.</hi> It reclaims as in ſin out of
<list>
                                                                        <item>malice when one ſins out of
<list>
                                                                              <item>deliberate counſel, &amp; deſtinate purpoſe of mind,</item>
                                                                              <item>affected ignorance: knowing in a confuſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit that the light would diſcover his evill work, Joh. 3.</item>
                                                                           </list>
                                                                        </item>
                                                                        <item>infirmity or weakneſs, but when one ſins
<list>
                                                                              <item>out of a certain knowledge and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the fact,</item>
                                                                              <item>frequently and neglects to correct it.</item>
                                                                           </list>
                                                                        </item>
                                                                     </list>
                                                                  </p>
                                                               </item>
                                                               <item>as it is bound. <hi>E.</hi>
                                                                  <p>
                                                                     <hi>E</hi> Is bound
<list>
                                                                        <item>by habit out, of which ſin proceeds
<list>
                                                                              <item>with greater deſire,</item>
                                                                              <item>more hard or difficult to be amended.</item>
                                                                           </list>
                                                                        </item>
                                                                        <item>by a frequent
<list>
                                                                              <item>rejection of him that admoniſhes,</item>
                                                                              <item>obſtinacy againſt him.</item>
                                                                           </list>
                                                                        </item>
                                                                     </list>
                                                                  </p>
                                                               </item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </p>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </p>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>the end. <hi>F.</hi>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>F.</hi> The end
<list>
                                          <item>Of the Agent,</item>
                                          <item>Of the thing, ſo far as out of the Hypotheſis of ſin God hath decreed, either
<list>
                                                <item>to forgive the penitent, through the death of his only begotten,</item>
                                                <item>to make the impenitent pay for it by eternal puniſhment.</item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </p>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. From the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<list>
                           <item>Poſitively in
<list>
                                 <item>The perſon of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<list>
                                       <item>inferring
<list>
                                             <item>the guilt,</item>
                                             <item>the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<list>
                                                   <item>always by deſerving it,</item>
                                                   <item>ſometimes by its crying</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>diſpoſing him to ſins
<list>
                                             <item>the ſame,</item>
                                             <item>other.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Others. <hi>A.</hi>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>A.</hi> Others
<list>
                                          <item>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<list>
                                                <item>the good
<list>
                                                      <item>the conſtant ones by grieving,</item>
                                                      <item>the weak ones, cauſing them to fall.</item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>the evill
<list>
                                                      <item>animating them,</item>
                                                      <item>cauſing them to
<list>
                                                            <item>blaſpheme
<list>
                                                                  <item>God,</item>
                                                                  <item>holy profeſſion.</item>
                                                               </list>
                                                            </item>
                                                            <item>defame
<list>
                                                                  <item>his friends,</item>
                                                                  <item>the reſt of the ſame profeſſion.</item>
                                                               </list>
                                                            </item>
                                                         </list>
                                                      </item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                          <item>Specially in
<list>
                                                <item>the preſent family,</item>
                                                <item>their poſterity.</item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </p>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Negatively
<list>
                                 <item>hindering future goods,</item>
                                 <item>taking away preſent goods.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. From the ſubject
<list>
                           <item>in which
<list>
                                 <item>it is received
<list>
                                       <item>externally,</item>
                                       <item>internally.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>it is placed
<list>
                                       <item>holy,</item>
                                       <item>common.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>about which it is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed.
<list>
                                 <item>the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<list>
                                       <item>Increated according to the various re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects and degrees of its manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in
<list>
                                             <item>our good
<list>
                                                   <item>willing it,</item>
                                                   <item>effecting it.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>aggravate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſin
<list>
                                                   <item>tolerating it,</item>
                                                   <item>hating it.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Created. <hi>A.</hi>
                                          <p>
                                             <hi>A.</hi> Created
<list>
                                                <item>Angels,</item>
                                                <item>Men
<list>
                                                      <item>Themſelves,</item>
                                                      <item>Their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours &amp; chiefly
<list>
                                                            <item>to him that is joyned
<list>
                                                                  <item>To God
<list>
                                                                        <item>by vertue,</item>
                                                                        <item>by office.</item>
                                                                     </list>
                                                                  </item>
                                                                  <item>To him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<list>
                                                                        <item>by nature in
<list>
                                                                              <item>conſanguinity,</item>
                                                                              <item>affinity,</item>
                                                                           </list>
                                                                        </item>
                                                                        <item>by
<list>
                                                                              <item>friendſhip,</item>
                                                                              <item>benefits
<list>
                                                                                    <item>freely beſtowed,</item>
                                                                                    <item>by covenant to be reſtored.</item>
                                                                                 </list>
                                                                              </item>
                                                                           </list>
                                                                        </item>
                                                                     </list>
                                                                  </item>
                                                               </list>
                                                            </item>
                                                            <item>to him that is moſt recommended to him by God, as
<list>
                                                                  <item>the aged,</item>
                                                                  <item>the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
<list>
                                                                        <item>any way,</item>
                                                                        <item>eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<list>
                                                                              <item>the ſtranger, the poor,</item>
                                                                              <item>the widow, the orphan, &amp;c.</item>
                                                                           </list>
                                                                        </item>
                                                                     </list>
                                                                  </item>
                                                               </list>
                                                            </item>
                                                         </list>
                                                      </item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </p>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>The thing. <hi>B.</hi>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>B.</hi> Of the thing
<list>
                                          <item>The Law
<list>
                                                <item>commanding,</item>
                                                <item>forbidding, againſt which we ſin moſt when we contrary it in the
<list>
                                                      <item>act,</item>
                                                      <item>object.</item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                          <item>The material ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, whether it
<list>
                                                <item>be
<list>
                                                      <item>holy,</item>
                                                      <item>common.</item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended
<list>
                                                      <item>by the ſenſe, as pleaſure,</item>
                                                      <item>by the mind, as
<list>
                                                            <item>wealth,</item>
                                                            <item>honours.</item>
                                                         </list>
                                                      </item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </p>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>IV. From the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct as well
<list>
                           <item>Of the ſinner out of
<list>
                                 <item>the reſpect
<list>
                                       <item>which he bears
<list>
                                             <item>in himſelf particularly, as he is a Chriſtian, having put on the new man.</item>
                                             <item>towards others, in a ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able one
<list>
                                                   <item>Publick,</item>
                                                   <item>Oeconomical.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>by which others are affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him
<list>
                                             <item>well as
<list>
                                                   <item>whom many honor, beleeve, and truſt.</item>
                                                   <item>from whom much good is expected.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>evill, that they may take
<list>
                                                   <item>leave to ſin,</item>
                                                   <item>occaſion to hurt
<list>
                                                         <item>by word,</item>
                                                         <item>by deed.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>the circumſtance of time. <hi>A.</hi>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>A.</hi> The cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time,
<list>
                                          <item>of the age, in which he ſins.</item>
                                          <item>of the action, by which he ſins in
<list>
                                                <item>quantity
<list>
                                                      <item>ſeverally ſo many times,</item>
                                                      <item>continually ſo long.</item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>relation to things then to be done
<list>
                                                      <item>ſacred
<list>
                                                            <item>ordinary,</item>
                                                            <item>extraordinary.</item>
                                                         </list>
                                                      </item>
                                                      <item>common
<list>
                                                            <item>of our ordinary vocation,</item>
                                                            <item>upon an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary occaſion.</item>
                                                         </list>
                                                      </item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </p>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Of ſin it ſelf. <hi>B.</hi>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>B.</hi> Of ſin it ſelf
<list>
                                    <item>with which he is clothed
<list>
                                          <item>privately, openly, &amp;c.</item>
                                          <item>hardly to be forgiven; the irremiſſible hath alſo place in the Dehortation.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>which is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſin
<list>
                                          <item>God,</item>
                                          <item>the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<list>
                                                <item>rationall
<list>
                                                      <item>Angels
<list>
                                                            <item>Good,</item>
                                                            <item>Bad.</item>
                                                         </list>
                                                      </item>
                                                      <item>Men of what relation ſoever.</item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>irrationall by howling.</item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </p>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>V. From the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant; where
<list>
                           <item>nothing is more frequent then the aggravation from the diverſe, See Chap. 9. Sect. 5.</item>
                           <item>oppoſite
<list>
                                 <item>vertue
<list>
                                       <item>one directly,</item>
                                       <item>the reſt extenſively.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in
<list>
                                       <item>other things, as if the ſin be againſt the command
<list>
                                             <item>forbidding care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe in the offices of Table
<list>
                                                   <item>firſt,</item>
                                                   <item>ſecond.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>commanding activity in
<list>
                                                   <item>evill things,</item>
                                                   <item>unneceſſary things.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>the ſame thing at another time.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>VI. From compared in
<list>
                           <item>quantity
<list>
                                 <item>equall,</item>
                                 <item>unequal,
<list>
                                       <item>the greater, if great, and which is not far from,</item>
                                       <item>the leſſer when it hath leſſe
<list>
                                             <item>vehemently diſpleaſed us,</item>
                                             <item>heavily been puniſhed.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>quality
<list>
                                 <item>ſemblable in evill,</item>
                                 <item>diſſemblable in good.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>VIII. From thoſe things that riſe either
<list>
                           <item>Nominal,</item>
                           <item>Real, where
<list>
                                 <item>the parts,</item>
                                 <item>the finition.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>VIII. From the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, where
<list>
                           <item>who
<list>
                                 <item>God who alſo ſometimes deſcends to our ways of
<list>
                                       <item>provoking.</item>
                                       <item>ſwearing.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Man by teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<list>
                                       <item>common
<list>
                                             <item>by the law,</item>
                                             <item>by the voice of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<list>
                                                   <item>included in
<list>
                                                         <item>a proverb,</item>
                                                         <item>a wiſe mans ſaying.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>ſpread abroad by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick report.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>proper.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>What.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:170289:98"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX. Of Conſolation or Comfort.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IF the Doctrine doth afford a Conſectary, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſome good to thoſe who are troubled and vexed in mind; this Conſectary muſt be applyed to the hearers in the uſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The formal object of this is either the evill of guilt or of puniſhment, which preſſeth the hearers either not at all, or not in ſuch a degree or meaſure, as they imagine. The end is to ſtir up joy. The means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he attains to this end, is by propounding to the heart ſome great and preſent good.</p>
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:170289:98"/>
               <p n="3">3. This preſence may be ſhewn by Notes taken from any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that neceſſarily infers the good which is propoſed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But becauſe in publick Sermons the uſual manner of comforting is, in ſpeaking to men, not plainly, but under that condition to which the Scripture promiſeth that good: Therefore becauſe thoſe ſhall not aſſume this comfort to whom it doth not belong (as not being endowed with that quality which is required) it will not be out of purpoſe ſometimes to give ſome notes by which one may judge of the preſence or abſence of that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and conſequently of the good which is thereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed.</p>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:170289:99"/>
               <p n="3">3. The reaſon of the good is
<list>
                     <item>Negative,</item>
                     <item>Poſitive.</item>
                  </list> The Negative good is in the abſence, of the all, or of ſo much of ſome evill (either of that which is thought to be preſent, or of ſome other), which if it were indeed preſent, would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict a man; but the abſence of it argues his affairs to be in a better condition, then he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. The Poſitive good tends to that, that if it cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the evill of puniſhment (as ſometimes it cannot) yet it may lenifie it and make it tolerable. But ſhews that the evill of ſin or guilt (becauſe that with it the good, and conſequently the comfort cannot conſiſt) may at leaſt be removed, and ſo far he may be comforted. But if it be
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:170289:99"/> demonſtrated that either the evill never was preſent, or that it is already removed, there ſeems no more to be required for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The rejoycing is by ſo much made the greater, by how much the good in it ſelf is greater, and the preſence of it is more ſtrict and apt for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation, and its perpetuity more firm.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The good may be ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied according to its nature. If it be a good of vertue, the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be fetched (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the rule of oppoſites) out of the Scheme of the aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of ſin. And this am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification may be extended ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more or leſſe, as his afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whom we intend to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, ſhall require. And the good is moſt of all to be ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170289:100"/> in that, wherein it is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to that evill which preſſeth the patient, either diminiſhing or removing, or preponderating of it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. As grief may ariſe out of an evill preſent, not only actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, but alſo in the certainty of the cauſes, ſo may joy out of a good. If therefore the object of fear doth urge vehemently, eſpecially according to a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of avoiding, ſo that it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quite take away, or too much weakens, that parcel of hope which is in the fear, and ſo cauſeth a grief and dejection of mind; The Conſolation may be either Negative, to the object of fear in that exceſſe, ſhewing that either there is no evill at all, or that it is not ſo great, or ſo unavoidable: or poſitive, by ſome good which is preſent, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:170289:100"/> actual, or in an equall or greater certitude of cauſes.</p>
               <p n="9">9. To this act may be added the act of Benediction, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of good.</p>
               <div type="cryptic">
                  <head>Crypſis.</head>
                  <p>The notes may alſo here be ſometimes omitted, eſpecially when they are taken from that condition or quality to which the good which is propounded is annexed, and the Preacher in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends inſtantly to exhort the Auditors unto it, for then in that exhortation (if ſo be it be abſolute in all its parts) there will be occaſion to make uſe of thoſe notes.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. The pronouncing of the bleſſing (as in the firſt uſe the Denuncitation of the cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:170289:101"/> the exerciſe of the Keyes, or ſeeming to make ſhew of ſome ſuch thing, doth therefore very well belong to the greateſt and weightieſt cauſes.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. He that comforts, doing it as Gods Miniſter, and in his Name, and out of ſome place of Scripture, peradventure out of the Hiſtory of ſome Heroick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon therein mentioned: and ſeeing thoſe who are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited doe more then ſeldom ſin through puſillanimity, grieving extreamly, and letting their minds faint upon ſlight occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to which the comfort is obvious, lying as it were before their feet: It may ſometimes be permitted to entermix Reproof, producing the examples of Chriſt, or Saints in Scriptures, who with alacrity and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Spirit did undergoe far
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:170289:101"/> greater afflictions. Which, if he think fitting, he may by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Proſopopoeia bring in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; they had cauſes of grief, equall to, if not greater then theirs, and laying forth by what means they hold out, rejoyced and ſang praiſes in their tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, looking upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and greatneſſe of the annexed good. And ſo at laſt conferring theirs, and his Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors condition, he may cloſe up this whole place, either up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding his hearers (if need be) with their ſoftneſſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becillity of mind, or exhorting them to imitate the fortitude of thoſe excellent men.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:170289:102"/>
               <head>CHAP. XX. Of Exhortation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. HItherto have been thoſe Uſes which have a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the heart, as being under a preſent diſtemper: now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thoſe which look upon it as in relation to ſome future thing. Theſe the Apoſtle ſeems to comprehend under the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe words [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>for inſtruction in righteouſneſſe,</hi> and they are
<list>
                     <item>Exhortation,</item>
                     <item>Dehortation.</item>
                  </list> Exhortation looks upon ſome future good, which belongs to
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:170289:102"/> the hearers, ſpuring on the heart to purſue it. The ſcope of this is to excite hope, or an effectual deſire: and propounds that which it exhorts unto, under the formal reaſon of the object of hope, which is, <hi>a future, ſublime or difficult, poſſible good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Motives are grounded upon the good of the thing to which they are exhorted. Which being conſidered in the degrees of ſubordination, which it hath to the <hi>ſummum bonum, or ſupreme good,</hi> as more or leſſe neceſſary for the attaining unto it; hath ſo much the more force, as the neceſſity is the greater: and moſt of all, if it be abſolutely neceſſary, by the neceſſity of the laſt end.</p>
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:170289:103"/>
               <p n="3">3. The good is
<list>
                     <item>honeſt and ſeemly,</item>
                     <item>uſeful and pleaſing.</item>
                  </list> To which may be added the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the evill, which may be taken for a good.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The good may be urged from the examples of God and Chriſt, and the examples of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels and men, from the good which is found in the ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational creature (as diligence or care in the Ant or Emmit, &amp;c.) from the good of men which are not good; and from the good alſo in the ſins of wicked, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, laborious men, &amp;c. in their generation, in doing evill; and that out of motions which are ſlight and weak (at leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively) if not quite null, but only in ſhew, and really
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:170289:103"/> diſſwaſive; Finally, from the examples of the Divels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, of which if a legion could agree in one man, much more is it juſt and fitting for two men to be perſwaded to live in concord in one houſe. To this part of Exhortation the Scheme may conduce.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To this act may be added a Commination, or Denuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of evill, as alſo a Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, (Jer. 13.17.) but Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothetically, if when they are pricked forward to ſome great good, they neglect to obey. In the ſame manner a bleſſing may be pronounced upon thoſe who ſtudiouſly ſeek after ſome great good.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If the hearers falſely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelves, that the good to which they are incited by the Exhortation, is not future, but
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:170289:104"/> that they are already poſſeſſed of it (the occaſion of ſuſpecting whereof in moſt of them may be the ſelf love which is bred in all men) ſome Notes may be given, whereby the abſence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may be argued. Neither will they be unuſeful, although it be truly preſent; for ſo the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives will incite to the cheriſhing of that good, and perſevering in it. But here the notes muſt not be taken from the cauſes, if that head of direct means muſt be treated of.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If the hearers have too confidently promiſed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they ſhall ever have in their power the thing it ſelf, or time to acquire it, ſo that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they will, without any trouble they may poſſeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of it, and ſo neglect the preſent then that which is
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:170289:104"/> hard muſt be expounded.</p>
               <p n="8">8. To obviate the firſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which is of the facility of the thing it ſelf, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider; Firſt, on Gods behalf the order which he hath fixed in things, according to which he would have every good thing, to not be acquired without la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and difficulty. Then on our part, how averſe our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved nature is from the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of excellent things. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how careful and aſſiduouſly Satan and his inſtruments en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, to deterre us from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering into the right way, or lead us another. As concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the other which is of the time or ſpace of gaining the thing; may be conſidered the contingency and incertitude of the future, as well concerning life, as capacity. Adde alſo the
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:170289:105"/> danger, either from Gods act, ſubſtracting his grace, and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth his decree: or from the efficacy of an evill cuſtom, which comes creeping in by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and encompaſſeth the mind with an hardneſſe, cauſing it no longer to obey wholeſome counſels and admonitions.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If the hearers ſhall judge the thing impoſſible, or too hard for them, Means may be added whereby that may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained whereunto we exhort them. In the treating of which, we may alſo obviate ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections (if any there be) by which men may ſeem to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred from ſeeking after that, which they believe they cannot attain to.</p>
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:170289:105"/>
               <p n="10">10. Means are of two kinds
<list>
                     <item>prohibiting by way of removing,</item>
                     <item>direct,</item>
                  </list> which (in the beginning of the action excited by the motives) doe inform (if need be) and teach the way of acting, and doe afford ſtrength to attain to, or effect that which we will. To all, each, or ſome of theſe (as it ſhall be convenient) may be added God's promiſes in Scriptures by which he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to thoſe who are willing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> power to uſe the means, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſucceſſe to thoſe who make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of them.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Sometimes before the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular aſſignation of the means, the general prae-requiſite ought to be premiſed, without which
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:170289:106"/> it is in vain to deliberate of the means; and which being laid both kinds of means may uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be preſcribed.</p>
               <div type="cryptic">
                  <head>Crypſis.</head>
                  <p n="12">12. When the chief Motives are contained in <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> they may here be omitted, and either others be applyed, or none at all: and the hearers be referred to <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>wherefore.</hi> Yet if the exhortation were of great moment, which was there propoſed to the mind <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>by way of teaching,</hi> and expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> way of reaſons, they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be uſefully reſumed, and being taken as for granted, urged to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ve affections.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. If the Auditors ſhall ſeem to be too great ſelf-pleaſers, ſo that the motives ſeem to be but little regarded by them, as ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:170289:106"/> to them, to not be very neceſſary: The Notes may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in the firſt place, then the Motives be added.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. That which is difficult, may here for the moſt part be omitted; as well becauſe it ſeems but accidentally to enter into the object of hope; as alſo becauſe ſloathful men uſe of their own accords to pretend difficulties, when they are incited to perform their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and finally becauſe the means doe in a manner pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe ſome hardneſſe. Yea oftentimes, in the Motives to urge a good, the argument muſt be drawn from the eaſineſſe: namely, when the means are omitted, or this argument is ſo handled, that it doth not fall in with them. But when it ſhall be neceſſary to touch it: the
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:170289:107"/> means may be ſo handled, as they may ſhew how theſe Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties may be overcome.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Becauſe mans heart is more prepared to the proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of good, by the apprehenſion of evill: The Preacher may ſometimes mixe Reprehenſion, and ſometimes Conſolation with the Exhortation, either in the beginning, or elſewhere, inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating how unſeemly it is for them now to need to have him exhort them to that, which they ſhould long ſince have perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of themſelves, &amp;c. Or that ſeeing ſuch an affliction lyeth upon them, there is now an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion proffered to exhort them to that which may countervail it abundantly, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:170289:107"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXI. Of Dehortation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. DEhortation hath a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſome future evil, to which the hearers are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious, or ſubject: inſtigating the heart to avoid and fly it. The ſcope of this is to excite fear; and therefore it repreſents that, from which it doth dehort, under the formal reaſon of the objected fear, that it <hi>is a great evill, imminent, avoidable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The grounds of Dehorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Diſſwaſives ought to be taken from the evill of that thing, from which we doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort? The Evill conſidered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its degrees and kinds, may be eſtimated by the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:170289:108"/> good, in the diſhoneſt and unſeemly; or the unuſeful, and diſpleaſing.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Evill may be urged here oppoſitely to the Good in the firſt act. There may alſo be added (if it be thought fitting) the difficulty or impoſſibility of ſatisfying the deſire in that matter. Though this ſeems to hinder the external act, rather then the root of fin which is in the heart: and tend more to proving the folly of man, then the iniquity of the thing.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To this may alſo be added (hypothetically) a Denunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or likewiſe a Lamentation, as alſo a Benediction, of which before: the Denuntiation againſt thoſe who follow, or doe not ſhun the evill which we dehort them from. The Benediction upon them which do fly from it.</p>
               <pb n="201" facs="tcp:170289:108"/>
               <p n="5">5. The imminency notes it to be future, and difficult. But here it is needleſſe to argue the future out of notes. For we uſe not eaſily (which is our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption) to imagine an evill to be preſent, when indeed it is preſent; much leſſe when it is future. For if it were preſent; then there would not be ſo much need of Dehortation, as of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, or Conſolation. Yet ſometimes there may be ſhewn (if it be thought expedient) out of the Notes, that the evill is yet abſent from the hearers, that they may be the better encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to avoid it as much as poſſibly as they can.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Difficult ſeems here to be eſſential to the object of fear, and therefore neceſſarily to be expounded; ſhewing the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquity of the evill which
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:170289:109"/> hangs over us, and preſſeth us, and the difficulty of ſhunning it. The difficulty may be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as well in reſpect of God, who doth ſo govern things by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, that occaſions of ſinning being offered us, our obedience may thereby be ſeen; and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, as alſo in reſpect of us, who as of our ſelves, are inclined to ſin and evill, ſo we are alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured and driven on thereunto by Satan and his inſtruments.</p>
               <p n="7">7. But on the otherſide the avoicablenſſe of the evill will appear, having laid open the means of avoiding it; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Gods promiſes, by which he promiſeth us, both the power of uſing means, and a ſucceſſe.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The means here, are either by removing the Illatives, or by avoiding thoſe things which may inferre the evill, that is to
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:170289:109"/> ſay, the cauſes of evill: or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring Prohibitives, or apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch things as can drive away the evill, that is to ſay, the cauſes of the contrary, or the contraries of the cauſes. Here alſo ſometimes there will be occaſion of premiſing the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral fore-requiſite, to avoid the Illatives, and bring in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatives.</p>
               <div type="cryptic">
                  <head>Crypſis.</head>
                  <p n="9">9. When <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>wherefore</hi> doth contain the chief Diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſives, we muſt doe as before in the Exhortation.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Here alſo may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what be intermixed out of the reſt of the Uſes that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce hereunto: as Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the abſence of the evil,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:170289:110"/> which may be argued from the the diſſemblable condition of other Congregations, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <pb facs="tcp:170289:110"/>
            <head>A Nomenclator of ſundry Tracts, Sermons, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, as may in ſome meaſure tend to make a skilful Laborer in the Lords Vineyard.</head>
            <list>
               <item>COmmentary on the whole Bible.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Engliſh</hi> Annotation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Diodate</hi> Annotation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roberts</hi> Key of the whole Bible.</item>
               <item>On Pentateuch, <hi>Henry Aynſworth,</hi> Mr. <hi>Trap, Arthur Jackson.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Geneſis, <hi>Willet, Shutt,</hi> and <hi>Wheatly.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Willet</hi> on Exodus &amp; Leviticus.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aterſol</hi> on Numbers.</item>
               <item>On Joſhua, <hi>Arthur Jackson, John Mayr.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Judges, <hi>John Mayr, Rich. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170289:111"/>
               <item>On Ruth, <hi>John Mayr, Thomas Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Samuel, <hi>John Mayr, An. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mayr</hi> on Kings, Chronicles, &amp; Ezra.</item>
               <item>On Nehemiah, <hi>John Mayr,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kington.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mayr</hi> on Eſther.</item>
               <item>On Job, <hi>Joſ Caryl, Calvin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Pſalms, <hi>Hen. Ainſworth, John Mayr, David Dixon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Proverbs, <hi>Jo. Dod.</hi> Dr. <hi>Jer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> Dr. <hi>Mayr, Fr. Taylor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Eccleſiaſtes, <hi>Hugh Broughton, Tho. Granger, Will. Pemble, Jo. Cotton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Canticles, <hi>Hen. Ainſworth, Thomas Brightman, John Cotton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robotham,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sibbs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Lamentations of Jeremiah, <hi>John <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dal, Broughton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Ezekiel, <hi>Will. Greenhill.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Daniel, <hi>Broughton, And. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170289:111"/> Mr. <hi>Huet, Parker.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the twelve minor Prophets, Dr. <hi>Mayr,</hi> Mr. <hi>Trapp,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Hoſea, Dr. <hi>Sibbs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Obadiah, Mr. <hi>Marbury.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Jonah, Biſhop <hi>King,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Abbot.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Habakkuk, <hi>Edw. Marbury.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Zachariah, <hi>Will. Pemble.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Malachi, <hi>Rich. Stork,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the New Teſtament, <hi>Thomas Cartwright,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hamond,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Leigh,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fulk.</hi> Mr. <hi>Trap.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Upon the four Goſpels, <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> Dr. <hi>Mayr, Jo. Trap.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Matthew, <hi>David Dixon,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Ward.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On S. Johns Goſpel, <hi>Arth. Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Acts, <hi>Joh. Mayr, Joh. Trap, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170289:112"/>
               <item>Upon the Epiſtles, <hi>Joh. Mayr, Joh. Trap.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Romans, <hi>Eliath. Parr,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wilſon, And. Willet, Elton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Epiſtles to the Corinth. Dr. <hi>Day, Will. Slater, T. Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Luther,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sibbs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the Galatians, <hi>Will. Perkins.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the Epheſians, <hi>Paul Bain.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the Colloſſians, <hi>Nich. Bifield, Edw. Elton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the Theſſalonians, <hi>W. Sclater.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To Timothy, <hi>Barlow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To Titus, <hi>Tho. Taylor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To Philemon, <hi>Arthur Sol. Dan. Dike.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Hebrews, <hi>Da. Dixon, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhington,</hi> Dr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Jones,</hi> Mr. <hi>Burroughs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the ſeven Canonical Epiſtles, <hi>Joh. Trap, John Mayr.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Epiſtle of James, Mr. <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Epiſtles of Peter, <hi>Nich.
<pb facs="tcp:170289:112"/> Bifield,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rogers,</hi> Mr. <hi>Adams, Will. Aymes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the firſt Ep. of John, <hi>J. Cotton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Epiſtle Jude, <hi>Sam. Oats, Will. Perkins, Will. Jenkins.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Revelation, <hi>Brightman, Dent, Will. Cooper, Forbi, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, Meed, Napier, Stevens.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Elaborate Sermons, B. <hi>Andrews,</hi> Mr. <hi>Burroughs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Carrill.</hi> D. <hi>Featly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gataker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> B <hi>Hall,</hi> Mr. <hi>Harris,</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Jackson,</hi> B. <hi>Lake,</hi> Mr. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> Dr. <hi>Preſton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Raynolds,</hi> D. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sibbs,</hi> M. <hi>Smith,</hi> Dr. <hi>Jeremy Taylor,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wheatly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Clark,</hi> Dr. <hi>Donn,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hen. Hamond.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Excent Catechiſms of the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>Veſcim,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ball,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Crook,</hi> &amp; B. <hi>Andrews</hi> Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſtical Doctrine, B. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170289:113"/>
               <item>On the Lords Prayer, B <hi>Andrews,</hi> Mr <hi>Dod,</hi> Dr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hen. King,</hi> M. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Creed, <hi>W. Bifield,</hi> Dr. <hi>Gill,</hi> Dr. <hi>Jackson, Perkins.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Decalogue, B. <hi>Andrews, Joh. Dod, Edw. Elton, W. Perkins.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, <hi>Jer. Dyke. W. Pemble,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> Dr. <hi>Preſton,</hi> D. <hi>Jer. Taylor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>R. Vines</hi> Sacramental Sermons.</item>
               <item>On Baptiſm, <hi>R. Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cobbet,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Featly, Tho. Fuller,</hi> Mr. <hi>Balley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Scripture and its Divine Authority, <hi>John Goodwin, John Weemes, Edw. Leigh, Sa. Heiſon,</hi> Mr <hi>Chappell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>N. Bifields</hi> Drection for reading Scripture.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jer Whites</hi> Way to the Tree of Life.</item>
               <item>Of God and his Attributes.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170289:113"/>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Jacksons</hi> Treatiſe of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Prestons</hi> Treatiſe of the Divine Eſſence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ric. Stork,</hi> on the Attributes.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Larkham</hi> on the Attributes.</item>
               <item>On Gods Providence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tho. Jackson,</hi> Dr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Providence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jo. Wilkins</hi> the Beauty of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</item>
               <item>On living and dying well. D. <hi>Jer. Taylor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Readings</hi> guid to the holy Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>N. Bifields</hi> Cure of fear of death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>S. Crook,</hi> Death Subdued.</item>
               <item>On Conſcience, M. <hi>Perkins,</hi> B. <hi>Hal, Jer. Dike, W. Fever,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hamond,</hi> Dr. <hi>Jer. Taylor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Sin, Mr. <hi>Bifield.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Tho. Goodwins</hi> Aggra. of Sin.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perks</hi> Great danger of little Sins.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> Sinfulneſſe of Sin.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170289:114"/>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Preſton,</hi> The Saints Infirmity.</item>
               <item>Of the Puniſhment of Sin.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Gouges</hi> Three Arrows.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tho. Beards</hi> Theater of Gods Judgements.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Clarks</hi> Looking-glaſſe for Saints and Sinners.</item>
               <item>On the Covenant of Grace, Dr. <hi>Preſton, John Cotton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>P. Burhley,</hi> the Goſpel Covenant.</item>
               <item>B <hi>Downham</hi> on the Covenant of Grace.</item>
               <item>Growth in Grace, Dr. <hi>Taylor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ob. Sedgwicks</hi> Chriſts Counſel to his Church.</item>
               <item>Mortification of Sin.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Preſtons</hi> Sins overthrow.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Wolfall,</hi> of Mortification.</item>
               <item>Of Juſtification, <hi>Wil. Pemble,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Downham, <hi>Jo. Goodwin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Aphoriſms of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</item>
               <item>Of Sanctification.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Preſtons</hi> Saints Qualification.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170289:114"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Joh. Downhams</hi> Spiritual Warfare.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> G. Worſhip.</item>
               <item>Of the four laſt things things, Death, Judgement, Heaven and Hell, <hi>Rob. Bolton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baxters</hi> Saints Reſt.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Shepheard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Generall Judgement, <hi>Greenwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>S. Smiths</hi> Great Aſſize.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Will. Fever,</hi> the Judgement of the World paſſed by Saints.</item>
               <item>On Perſeverance.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ob. Sedgwick,</hi> on Rev. 3.2. &amp; 3.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Arth. Burgeſſe</hi> Spiritual Refinings.</item>
               <item>Dr <hi>Owen</hi> in anſwer to <hi>J. Goodwin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Kendall,</hi> Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> Heaven on Earth.</item>
               <item>On Prayer, <hi>R. Harris.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peters</hi> Inlargement.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Preſtons</hi> Saints dayly exerciſe.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Cobbet, Jo. Wilkins,</hi> B. <hi>Prideux</hi> Legacy to his Daughters.</item>
               <item>Return of Prayer, <hi>Tho, Goodwin.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170289:115"/>
               <item>Hearing and reading the Word, Mr. <hi>Maſon, Jer. Dyke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>B. <hi>Andrews</hi> on James 1.22.</item>
               <item>On the Love and Fear of God.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Preſton</hi> of Love.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Will. Pemble,</hi> the Chriſtians Love.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pincks,</hi> triall of a Chriſtian Love.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Harris, David</hi> comfort at <hi>Zik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Greenham,</hi> of Gods Fear.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Will. Caſe,</hi> the Nature and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of godly fear.</item>
               <item>On the Sabbath, Dr. <hi>Twiſt, Phil. Goodwin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Sabbath enlivened, M. <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard, Primreſs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caudy</hi> and <hi>Palmer</hi> in four parts.</item>
               <item>Of Sacriledge and Tithes, B. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> B. <hi>Carlton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Spelman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Political and Oeconomical Duties.</item>
               <item>B. <hi>Halls</hi> Politicks.</item>
               <item>B. <hi>Bilſon</hi> on Subjection.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170289:115"/>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> of the right manner of Governing a Family.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Dods</hi> Houſhold Government.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Gouges</hi> Domeſtical Duties.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Cobbet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Government of the Tongue, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Reyner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Boltons</hi> Direction.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Perkins</hi> government of tongue.</item>
               <item>Of our Thoughts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tho. Graper,</hi> Govern. of Thoughts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tho. Goodwin,</hi> Vanity of thoughts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>W. Fever,</hi> the Araignment of Vain thoughts.</item>
               <item>Of Contentation, Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> B. <hi>Hall,</hi> Mr. <hi>Watſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Faith, Dr. <hi>Preſton, Tho. Ball, Jer. Culverwell,</hi> Dr. <hi>Jackson.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>T. Goodwins</hi> Encourag. of Faith.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Perk.</hi> Grain of Muſtard-ſeed.</item>
               <item>On Repentance, Dr. <hi>Tho. Taylor,</hi> Dr. <hi>Jer. Taylor, Dan. Dyke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Preſtons Judas</hi> Repentance.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170289:116"/>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Hamond</hi> of Late Repentance.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>W. Fever,</hi> Danger of defering Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</item>
               <item>On True Converſion.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Shepards</hi> Sincere Convert.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Shepards</hi> Sound Beleever.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> Soul Preparation,</item>
               <item>— Humiliation,</item>
               <item>— Vocation,</item>
               <item>— Exaltation,</item>
               <item>— Implantation.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Cottons</hi> Way of Life.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
